<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons preached at the assises holden at Carlile touching sundry corruptions of these times / by L.D. ...</title>
            <author>Dawes, Lancelot, 1580-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 209 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19954</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6389</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S320</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22270954</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22270954</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25300</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19954)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25300)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1750:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons preached at the assises holden at Carlile touching sundry corruptions of these times / by L.D. ...</title>
                  <author>Dawes, Lancelot, 1580-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 146, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: [par.]⁴ A-I⁸ K².</note>
                  <note>Errors in paging: p. 133 and 145 misnumbered 127 and 121 respectively.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Glasgow. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25300:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25300:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO SERMONS PREACHED AT the Aſſiſes holden at CARLILE, <hi>tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching ſundry corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of theſe times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By L. D. ſometimes fellow of Queenes Coll. <hi>in Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISAIAH 62.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For Sions ſake, will I not hold my peace.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by Ioſeph Barnes. 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:25300:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25300:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REND FATHER IN God the Lord Biſhop of CARLIL.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT RE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EREND,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I preached at <hi>Carlil</hi> at the laſt Aſſiſes, I made no other account, but that my ſermon ſhould (like Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles<note n="a" place="margin">Ariſt. de hiſt. animal. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>19</hi>
               </note> Ephemeron) haue died the ſame day that it tooke breath. Since which time I haue beene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated by diverſe to make it common: to whom I would not yeeld the least aſſent, as doubting that their deſires proceeded ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from affection towards the speaker, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from a ſound iudgement of the things spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. But when I perceived how diſtaſtfull it was to ſome, that beare Romiſh hearts in Engliſh breaſts; I reſolved, as <hi>David</hi> did whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Micol</hi> mocked him for dancing before the arke, to <hi>be yet more vile,</hi> by publiſhing that vnto their eies, which before was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to their eares; hoping that the more
<pb facs="tcp:25300:3"/> it diſpleaſeth them the better acceptance it ſhall finde with the true Iſraelite. Which now at length I haue effected. So that as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they heard it (or at leaſt heard of it) ſo now they may read it. And <hi>if I haue evill ſpoken let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beare witneſſe of the evil, but if I haue ſaid wel, why do they ſmite me?</hi> It ſeems to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a meere calumniation to ſay that there is no probability that a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt ſhall liue peaceably with vs, &amp; performe true and ſincere obedience towardes our Prince. To whom I might returne the ſhort anſwere of the <hi>Lacones</hi> to their adverſary, <hi>Si:</hi> if it were ſo, my speech was not to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, becauſe not only rebels to the king, but much more to God and his true worſhip and ſervice, are to be rooted out of a Chriſtian commonwealth. And if thoſe bee worthy a ſharpe cenſure which agreeing vvith vs in the fundamentall points of Divinity, cannot away with the <hi>carved worke of our tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> but cut it downe as it were with axes &amp; hammers: how much more thoſe <hi>Sanballats</hi> and <hi>Tobiahs,</hi> that ſtrike at the foundation thereof, and ſay of it, as did the children of <hi>Edom in the day of Ieruſalem, down with it, downe with it, even to the ground.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I rather ſay, <hi>O ſi,</hi> I wiſh it were ſo, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:25300:3"/> that there were no feare of danger by their meanes and deviſes. But this I doubt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be effected, vnleſſe there be, I will not ſay with the Oratour, a <hi>wal,</hi> but a <hi>ſea</hi> betweene them and vs. Till then there is as great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of peace betweene vs as there was of old betweene the Catholikes and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts, the Orthodoxall and the Arians, the Hebrewes and the Egyptians, the Iewes and the Samaritans:
<q>Immortale odium &amp; nunquam ſana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile vulnus.</q> And for true loialty, and faithful obedience there is as great probability, as that the two poles ſhall meete. The King and the Pope are two contrary maſters none can truely ſerue them both; <hi>Either he muſt hate the one, and loue the other, or he muſt leane to the one and deſpiſe the other.</hi> The obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience which either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> requires is ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant, that they cannot lodge within one breſt. This loialty which our adverſaries do outwardly pretende is but equivocall, no more true loialty, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a dead hand is a hand; it wants the very forme and ſoule (if I may ſo speake) of true dutifulneſſe, which is to performe obedience voluntarily and with a free heart for Gods cauſe, as to Chriſts im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate
<pb facs="tcp:25300:4"/> Vicar over all perſons within his dominions. It is with ſome ſecret reſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, till their <hi>primus motor,</hi> the man of ſin, vpon whom their obedience depends, ſhall ſway them an other way: or <hi>rebus ſic ſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> the ſtate ſtanding as it doth, &amp; <hi>donec publica bullae executio fieri poſſit,</hi> vntill they may haue power and ſtrength to reſiſt. So that I may vſe the ſame words vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which <hi>Auſtin</hi> doth to the Rogatists,<note place="margin">Aug. ep. <hi>48.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Saevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re vos nolle dicitis, ego non poſſe arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tror; ita enim eſtis numero exigui, vt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere vos contra adverſarias vobis multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudines non audeatis, etſi cupiatis.</hi> I ſpeak chiefly of ſuch as are grounded in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Popiſh divinity, &amp; take for current whatſoever is ſtamped in Romes mint. As for their ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t followers I only giue them that cenſure, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> giues the Iews; <hi>They haue the zeale of God, but not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to knowledge, for they being ignorant of the righteouſneſſe of God, &amp; going about to ſtabliſh their owne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, haue not ſubmitted themſelues to the righteouſneſſe of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haue adventured to ioine with this an other Sermon preached before vpon a like occaſion (ſo farre as I could gather it out of
<pb facs="tcp:25300:4"/> a few ſcattered papers flying abroad like <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>billa's</hi> leaues,
<q>—rapidis ludibria ventis.</q> Which I haue the rather done, becauſe my experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce theſe few years in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, hath taught me how commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe ſins are which I haue herein endeavoured to reproue. If theſe my labours ſhall not bee diſtaſtfull, I ſhall bee willing to goe forward in a greater ſubiect. Howſoever they ſhall be taken, I ſubmit them to the cenſure of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and of everie indifferent Reader (not counting what carping <hi>Momus</hi> can ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) in the words of iudicious <hi>Vives;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lud. Vives in Auguſt. de de Civit Dei li. vlt. c. vlt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>Si quid dixi quod placeat, habeat lector gratiam Deo propter me; ſi quid quod no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> placeat, ignoſcat mihi propter Deum &amp; malè dictis det veniam propter benè dicta;</hi> and of holy <hi>Auſtin</hi> in the concluſion of his long diſcourſe <hi>de Trinitate, Domine Deus vnus &amp; trinitas, quaecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dixi de tuo agnoſcant &amp; tui, ſi qua de meo &amp; tu ignoſce &amp; tui.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips in Chriſt to be commaunded <hi>LANCELOT DAWES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:25300:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25300:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATH. 26.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>What will yee giue me, and I will deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him vnto you?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> haue elſewhere, in a great and popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous auditory, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours mildnes, &amp; humility, &amp; of the deceit and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie of the Iudaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of theſe times, from theſe words of our Saviour: <hi>Iudas betrayeſt thou the ſon of man with a kiſſe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 22.48<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> Being commanded to ſupply this place, I thought it not vnfit for this preſent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, to looke backe into the ſtorie of our Saviours paſſion, &amp; to ſeeke out the cauſe of <hi>Iudas</hi> his cruell, and more then helliſh fact, in betraying his Maſter, which I finde wrapped in the wordes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready delivered vnto you.</p>
            <p>Theſe two queſtions, <hi>what wil yee giue
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:25300:6"/> me?</hi> and what <hi>ſhal I giue you?</hi> be two evils at this day much reigning amongſt men; which though they may ſtand ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what vpon their antiquity, yet they haue little reaſon to bragge of their petigree. For the one may be fathered vpon <hi>Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Magus,</hi> who offered to buy the gifts of the holy Ghoſt for mony:<note place="margin">Act. 8.19.</note> 
               <hi>What ſhall I giue you, that vpon whomſoever I ſhall lay my hands, he may receiue the holy Ghoſt?</hi> the other vpon <hi>Iudas</hi> the traitour, who offered to ſel the giver of the holy Ghoſt for a ſmall ſumme of mony. <hi>What will yee giue mee, and I will deliver him vnto you?</hi> Both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wicked, but the ſpeech of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>das</hi> the more hainous. Who not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with that which he gat by ſtealth out of the bag which he bare, and being diſappointed of a profit which he expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in regard that that boxe of oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which hee purpoſed to haue ſold, (that he might haue converted a good part thereof to his own proper vſe,) was powred vpon our Saviours head: &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving our Saviour to defend the fact of the woman, anone hee goes out; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee was fruſtrated of his hope of gaine by ſelling the ointment, he offers
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:25300:6"/> for a ſmall ſumme of mony to ſell the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed. <hi>What will yee giue mee, and I will deliver him vnto you?</hi> As if he ſhould haue ſaid, I perceiue that yee are marveilous deſirous to apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d my maſter, but yee ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not eaſilie effect your purpoſe, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the people, which make ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of him, that percha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce they would make an vproare, if any open violence ſhould be offered vnto him: yet if yee wil liſten vnto me, and follow my counſell, I wil quickly eaſe you of that care, vpon this condition, that yee will afford mee any reaſonable reward for my paines; tel me therefore before I go, what ſhall my recompence bee, and I will vndertake without any tumult to deliver him into your hands. In which wordes obſerue theſe two points, 1. <hi>Iudas</hi> his queſtion, <hi>what will yee giue mee?</hi> 2. His promiſe to deliver his maſter, ſo that he may bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded: <hi>and I will deliver him vnto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the queſtion wee ſee, that though <hi>Iudas</hi> was an Apoſtata, fallen from God, and ledde by Satan to betray his maſter, whom he little eſteemed, as appeares by the price he ſold him for; yea though hee had a deſire to make his maſter away,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25300:7"/> leaſt hee ſhould afterward get knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his theft, yet hee will not betray him vnleſſe hee haue ſomething for his paines. And therefore before he make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny promiſe of delivering him, hee cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanteth for a price: whence ariſeth this note, <hi>that even the wicked, and reprobate will abſtaine from horrible and groſſe ſinnes when there is no provocation offered, and when they ſee no end of committing them.</hi> There are in every ſinne which is volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily committed two cauſes. An inward impulſiue mouing them; and ſomething which may haue the name of a final cauſe or elſe an external obiect, alluring them. The impulſiue cauſe in <hi>Iudas</hi> was covet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. The finall cauſe was to obtaine ſome mony. The impulſiue cauſe kept it ſelfe cloſe, and like a theefe, lurked in a corner, til a fit opportunitie was offered, and a reward was expected. As it was in <hi>Iudas,</hi> ſo was it in <hi>Achan;</hi> no doubt but <hi>Achan</hi> had giuen lodging to covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe before the overthrowe of <hi>Iericho:</hi> but then he had the opportunitie offered him. He ſaw amongſt the ſpoile a goodly <hi>Babyloniſh garment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. 7.21.</note> 
               <hi>and two hundred ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles of ſilver, &amp; a wedge of gold, &amp; becauſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25300:7"/> he coveted them hee tooke them</hi> (contrarie to the Lords commandment) <hi>&amp; hid them in the midſt of his tent.</hi> As it was in theſe two, ſo was it in <hi>Gehazi.</hi> I make no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion but an inordinate deſire of hauing had poſſeſſed his heart, before that <hi>Naa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> the Syrian, came to his maſter, to be healed of his leaproſie. But never ſuch an opportunitie was offered, as was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaw <hi>Naama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> offer his maſter ſome rich rewards for curing him, &amp; his maſter abſolutely refuſing them,<note place="margin">2. Kin. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 20.</note> hee thought then was the golden occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> offered him to ſatiate his greedy deſires, &amp; therefore poſts after <hi>Naaman</hi> to get ſomething of him. Wicked <hi>Ahab</hi> who (as the holy Ghoſt ſpeaketh) <hi>ſold himſelfe to worke wickedneſſe,</hi> did not ſhedde the blood of <hi>Naboth</hi> the Iſraelite, but to this ende, that hee might obtaine the vineyard which lay neere vnto his houſe. Now as it is in covetouſneſſe, ſo with other ſins. And the reaſon is very plain: for though the vnderſtandings of the wicked bee ſo darkned, that they call <hi>good evill, and evil good, ſower ſweet, and ſweet ſower;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 5.</note> though their appetites and affections bee ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, that they ſwallow vp ſinne with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:25300:8"/> greedineſſe, &amp; drinke iniquitie like wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: yet there is ſome reliques of the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God in their vnderſtanding, whereby they haue a glimpſe of good &amp; evill, which though it cannot moderate the will, and affections from running in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſinne, yet it doth ſo farre forth bridle them, as that they will not commit any hainous impietie, but when ſome thing is offered which puts as it were a vizard vpon the obiect of the will, and makes it chuſe that which otherwiſe it would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe. For the will by nature is alwaies ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried vnto his proper obiect, which is good, and abhorreth that which is evill. So that when it chuſeth evill, it is not as it is a will, but as it is depraved, &amp; as the vnderſtanding, which iudgeth of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, before the will chooſe or refuſe it, cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth that good which indeed is evill. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> 3 Here two ſorts of men are to be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured: the firſt is ſuch as think themſelues ſufficiently excuſed for committing any ſinne, if they can bring any occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or the allurements which haue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them to commit it. The drunkard will ſay that company hath drawne him to forget himſelfe, and therefore hee
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:25300:8"/> muſt bee pardoned. The adulterer will plead for himſelfe, that his owne corrupt affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath moved him, &amp; that the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtances of time &amp; place haue cauſed him, and therefore he muſt bee excuſed. But theſe excuſes are ſuch, as that, if they would ſerue the turne, the wickedeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate vpon the face of the earth might be found not guilty. For might not <hi>Iudas</hi> haue pleaded for himſelfe, that he would never haue betraied Chriſt, but that hee expected ſome rewarde from the high Prieſts? Might not <hi>Ahab</hi> haue ſworne that hee woulde never haue ſought <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boths</hi> blood, if it had not bin for his vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarde which was ſo commodious for his houſe? Might not <hi>Achan</hi> haue avouched that he would never haue tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſed the Lords commandement by taking of the excommunicate thing, but that it ſo offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it ſelfe that he thought he might haue taken it, and none bin privy to it? Might not <hi>Cain</hi> haue excuſed the ſlaughter of his guiltleſſe brother, that he woulde not haue killed him, if the Lord had not had a greater reſpect vnto <hi>Abels</hi> ſacrifice, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto his? It is true indeed, that ſuch ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects may occurre, ſuch induceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts may
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25300:9"/> happen, as that the deareſt of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (which as long as they remaine in theſe houſes of clay do taſt too much of the old <hi>Adam</hi>) may thereby be led to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit groſſe impieties. We know, that the feare of death mooved <hi>Peter</hi> to deny his Maſter: That idlenes, &amp; the ſight of <hi>Bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba,</hi> cauſed <hi>David</hi> to adultery: That <hi>Lots</hi> daughters brought their father to commit inceſt: That <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> by his wiues was drawne to Idolatry: That the fear of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> made faithfull <hi>Abraham</hi> to diſtruſt Gods providence, &amp; to ſay that his wife was his ſiſter. But this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onely ſhews their imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; it excuſeth not their facts, that they had ſundry provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to theſe ſins. If <hi>Peter</hi> had thought that the feare that the Iews put him in, by reaſon of the great cruelty which they v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt his maſter, might haue excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him for denying Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> he might haue ſpared his teares. If occaſion, and time &amp; place, might haue purchaſed a pardon for <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.1.</note> he would never haue been ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement, and paſſionate, in confeſſing his fault, and craving a pardon for the ſame. And indeed this is the only courſe to be freed from Gods plagues, not to excuſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25300:9"/> our ſinnes, and ſay that ſuch &amp; ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations brought vs to them: for ſo the wickedeſt reprobate might be innocent) but to humble our ſelues before the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of God, and to confeſſe our miſery, that he may receiue vs to mercy.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> 4 There is another ſort of men which if they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit not ſuch iniquities as others do, (either becauſe their natures are not ſo prone, and bent to thoſe vices, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch obiectes and allurements are wanting, as others haue had) will boaſt (at leaſt within the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues) that they haue attained vnto a farre greater meaſure of holineſſe, then others, which by their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall proneneſſe, or ſome external cauſe, are drawne to wickednes. But (alas) what credit is it for the Scythians, that they were no drunkards, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they never gate wine nor ſtrong drinke? What commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for the olde <hi>Germanes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tacit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that they abſtained from the vnlawfull companie of women, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by nature they were not addicted to wantonnes? What credit is it for a yong childe, or withered old man, to abſtaine from carnall pleaſure, when the heate of youth in the one is quelled, &amp; the other never knew what luſt meant?
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:25300:10"/> What grace for a weak ſpirited ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who was never moved with any exceſſiue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, not to be a murtherer? This is rather commendatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worthy, if we ſhall abſtain fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe vices to which our corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth moſt propend: If the Dutch can leaue his drunkennes, the Italian his luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, the French his factiouſnes, the Spaniard his hautineſſe, the Engliſh his gluttony, &amp; greedines: if the cholericke can lay aſide his anger, and raſhneſſe; the phlegmaticke his ſloath, &amp; idleneſſe; the melancholicke his hatred, &amp; enviouſnes; the ſanguine his concupiſcence, and wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonnes; in a word, if <hi>Herod</hi> can be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to part with <hi>Herodias,</hi> and every man his beloved ſin, to which by nature he is moſt addicted.</p>
            <p>When a certaine Phyſiognomer loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vpon <hi>Socrates,</hi> gathered by his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion that he was given to l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt &amp; wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, the people which knewe the continencie, and vertuous life of <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> mocked him as vnskilfull of his art, thinking that <hi>Socrates</hi> was not addicted to any ſuch vice. But <hi>Socrates</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the iudgement of the Phyſiogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer to be true, and confeſſed that by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:25300:10"/> diſpoſition hee was prone vnto it; thinking it a greater vertue to conquer, and keepe vnder the corruptions of the fleſh; then to keepe himſelfe vnder, and within the bond of reaſon, when hee had nothing to draw him away. And yet this is little worth, vnleſſe it be at ſuch time, when ſome externall meanes, and provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations doe concurre, for bringing that into act, which depraued nature moſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth. The drunkard will ſometimes abſtaine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his beaſtlineſſe: but it is whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he can get no wine. The oppreſſer from grinding, and grating the faces of the poore; but it is when hee lacks matter to worke vpon. The wanton from his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; but it is when hee wants time, and place to effect his deſires. The glutto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his exceſſiue cating: but it is in a dearth, or ſcarcitie, when he knowes not how to fill his p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unch. It had been praiſe worthy in <hi>Iudas,</hi> if hauing a covetous minde, the high Prieſt had come vnto him, and offered him a large ſumme of mony, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this condition, that hee would haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed his maſter; and he ſhould haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, as <hi>Simon Peter</hi> did to <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus: your mony periſh with you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 8.20.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe yee
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:25300:11"/> thinke that the ſonne of God may be bought for mony.</hi> It is a good commendation which <hi>Tully</hi> giues to <hi>Muraena,</hi> that living amongſt the effeminate and luxurious Aſians, hee was not infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with their faultes. <hi>Laus illi tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Orit pro Mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aena.</note> 
               <hi>non quòd Aſiam viderat, ſed quòd in Aſia continenter vixerat.</hi> And <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> deſerues the name of a ſober and temperate man, not becauſe hee was ſo amongſt the Grecians, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee kept himſelfe ſober in <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> cellar; where all his fellowes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Eurylochus</hi> were drunke. On the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y it argueth weakneſſe in <hi>Anacharſis</hi> the Scythia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Philoſopher (who vſed to ſay in commendation of his countrey that there were no<note n="a" place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt. Poſt. Analyt. lib. <hi>1</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pipers in Scythia be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there were no vines</hi>) that fallng into the company of ſome Cellar-knights which dranke for a wager, he tooke their part, and was fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt drunke vnder boord himſelfe.<note place="margin">Pſal. 11.5.</note> The Lord, ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>trieth the righteous.</hi> Hee ſuffereth ſuch obiects to bee offered vnto them, as may be allurements vnto ſinne; that by refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing &amp; forſaking thereof, they may make
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:25300:11"/> it knowne to the world, to whom they belong. So was <hi>Lots</hi> righteouſnes tried, not when hee dwelled with <hi>Abraham,</hi> but when hee was remoued to <hi>Sodome:</hi> which though it was for the pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſoyle like the <hi>garden of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> yet for wickedneſſe and vnnaturall vncleaneneſſe it ſurmounted hell it ſelfe. And yet for all this it could not infect <hi>righteous Lot, who dwelling amongſt them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>from day to day vexed his righteous ſoule by their vnlawfull deeds.</hi> So was <hi>Davids</hi> innocencie tried, not when he fled from <hi>Saul,</hi> but when he found him aſleepe and might haue killed him.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 26<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> So likewiſe thou declareſt thy righteouſneſſe, not when thou abſtaineſt from ſuch ſinnes as thy nature is averſe from, or from ſuch ſinnes as thy fleſh is prone vnto, at ſuch times as fit meanes are wanting to accompliſh thy deſire: but when thou abſtaineſt from ſuch as thy fleſh inwardly deſireth, and ſome externall provocation vrgeth and allureth thee vnto. Thou muſt, when the high Prieſt offers thee a rich reward, not be bribed to ſell thy maſter. With <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> thou muſt liue ſober
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:25300:12"/> at <hi>Cyrces table,</hi> with <hi>Lot</hi> thou maiſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt honeſt amongſt the <hi>Sodomites:</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if thou perſwadeſt thy ſelfe, that thou doſt well, if thou canſt abſtain from groſſe ſinnes, when there is no great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement to perſwade thee to act them; this is but <hi>Iudas</hi> his righteouſneſſe, who would not betray his maſter but in hope of reward, <hi>what will yee giue me, and I will deliuer him vnto you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 And ſo I come vnto the ſecond ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall part: wherein obſerue 1. the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> delivering, <hi>I.</hi> 2. the action, <hi>deliver.</hi> 3. the partie delivered, <hi>him.</hi> 4. the parties to whom, <hi>vnto you.</hi> Of which before I parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly intreat we may from the promiſe as it hath reference vnto the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>That a couetous mind, ſetting all reſpects aſide, will not be afraid to commit any ſinne, ſo that hee may bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded for his paines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 22.2.</note> and <hi>Iohn</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh 13 3.</note> tell vs, that the Devill put it into the heart of <hi>Iudas</hi> to betray his maſter. He put it not into the heart of <hi>Peter,</hi> or <hi>Iohn,</hi> or any other of the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; why? becauſe this <hi>Philargyria,</hi> had only taken root in <hi>Iudas</hi> his heart: the reſt were not infected with this diſeaſe.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:25300:12"/> They were indeed weak, &amp; feeble in the faith, and therefore <hi>Peter</hi> though he fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him a far of, &amp; came into the high Prieſts hall, yet a poore damſell did ſo ſhake the rock of his faith, that preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he denied him, the reſt immediatly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he was taken forſooke him, and fled: but none of them did entertain any ſuch ſuggeſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as to betray him, ſaue <hi>Iudas Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cariot,</hi> who before was entangled with the chaynes &amp; fetters of covetouſnes. So true is it which the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>thoſe that will be rich fall into ſnares and tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the devil;</hi> for ſo the vulgar addeth 1 Tim. 6.4. Here then, if ever, the poets exclamation may haue place,
<q>
                  <l>—Quid non mortalia pectora cogis<note place="margin">Aen. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Auri ſacra fames!—</l>
               </q> What vice ſo ſcandalous; what thing ſo monſtrous; what ſinne to God &amp; nature ſo odious, which the deſire of mony will not cauſe a man to commit? A man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayeth a man, a ſervant his maſter, a crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture delivers his creator, the<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 17.12</note> ſonne of perdition<note n="b" place="margin">Matth. 16.16.</note> the ſonne of God; the Lord of life muſt bee put to death for a little mony. Well therefore doth the Apoſtle tearme <hi>covetouſneſſe the roote of all evill.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.10</note>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:25300:13"/> For as al the lines of a circle do take their beginning from one middle point or ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; ſo all other evils doe ſpring from this fountaine.<note place="margin">Gal 5.20.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> 
               <hi>The workes of the fleſh are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>which are Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, witchcraft, hatred, debate, emulations, wrath, contentions, ſeditions, hereſies, envy, murther;</hi> I may adde lying, ſwearing, ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, oppreſſing, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce do they proceed, but from a covetous &amp; infatiable heart? This is the wombe where they ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are bred.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aven.</note>—Lucri bonus eſt odor ex re</l>
               <l>Qualibet—</l>
            </q>
            <p>ſaith the Poet: alluding to the fact of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spaſian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sueton in Veſpaſiano.</note> in <hi>Suetonius,</hi> who gathered a taxe from ſome homely matters, and tolde his ſonne <hi>Titus</hi> that it ſmelled as wel, as any other ſilver did. Be it gotten, by theft, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſtealing, ſwearing, forſwearing, vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, oppreſſion, what way ſo ever it bee gotten, (ſaith the covetous in his heart) if it be gaine, it is wel gotten. <hi>Tacitus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tacit. hiſt. l. <hi>3</hi>
               </note> tels vs of a <hi>Roman</hi> knight, that killed his own brother, in hope to be rewarded for his paines. Hiſtories are full of the like, which I will paſſe over with ſilence. I wil only inſtance in one of our owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:25300:13"/> (which me thinkes in all points, ſaue in the difference of the parties betrayed, may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to this of <hi>Iudas</hi>) I meane <hi>Humfery Baniſter</hi> ſervant to the Duke of <hi>Buckingham:</hi> whom the Duke had ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly brought vp, and aboue all loued &amp; truſted, inſomuch that being purſued by K. <hi>Richard</hi> the third, hee hid himſelfe in <hi>Banisters</hi> houſe, thinking it to bee the only ſanctuary, where he might ſafely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelfe. But wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n K. <hi>Richard</hi> had promiſed 1000 pounds to thoſe that would finde him out, the deſire of gaine ſo wrought with him, that preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly he be trayed his Lord &amp; maſter into the kings hands. As the fact was like to that of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> ſo the puniſhment hath ſome reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance with it. <hi>Iudas</hi> though hee had no bond for payment, yet he got the mony. The high Prieſts proued better of their promiſe then the King <hi>Iudas</hi> did not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the mony, for he went out,<note place="margin">In the life of Richard the 3 writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by Sir Th. More.</note> and han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged himſelfe. <hi>Baniſter</hi> was not executed, but was ſhortly after for a murther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned: his ſonne &amp; heire became mad, and died in a hogſtie, his daughter was infected with a leproſie, his ſecond ſon deformed of his limmes; his youngeſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:25300:14"/> ſonne drowned in a puddle.</p>
            <p n="6">6 By this wh ch hath been ſpoken, you ſee my concluſion plainely proved: that a covetous man, ſetting al reſpects aſide, will not be afrayd to commit any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nne, ſo that hee may bee rewarded for his paines. And how can it be otherwiſe? for hee is like a hunger-ſtarved man which will doe any thing, ſo that he may ſatiate his appetite. Covetouſneſſe like the pit of hell, is never ſatisfied, and like the bar ren wombe, it never ſaith, I haue enough.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ovid. Faſt.</hi> Prov. 30 15</note>
               <hi>Quo plus ſunt potae, plus ſitiuntur aquae. the more blood the two daughters of the horſeleech ſhal ſucke, the more eagerly they cry out<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Hor.</note> 
               <hi>giue. giue.</hi> This barren &amp; dry earth is never ſatisfied with water; <hi>nec ſitim pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit, niſi cauſa morbi.</hi> Nothing will content this dropſie, but that which more aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth the diſeaſe, as nothing will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the fire, but that which more aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth the flame. Hee is like vnto him that hath the <hi>Caninus appetitus,</hi> the more he eateth the more he hungreth. Some Phyſitians ſay that gold is good for him that is in a conſumption, but I never read that it is good againſt a ſurfeit. But expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience proues it true that a gold-hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:25300:14"/> man, doth not onely long for this mettall when he is in a conſumption, but farre more when hee hath taken a ſurfeit through abundance.</p>
            <q>—congeſto pauper in auro eſt.</q>
            <p>The richer, the poorer: his mind hunger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as much for gold, as <hi>Dionyſius</hi> his belly hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gred for fleſh, who vſed to ſtand all the day in the ſhambles, <hi>&amp; quod eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re non potuerat, oculis devorabat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iuſtin. l. <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> That which he could not buy with his pennie, he devoured with his eies. And here that comes in my minde which <hi>Herodotus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordeth of <hi>Alcmaeon</hi> the <hi>Athenian,</hi> who becauſe hee had kindly entertained the meſſengers which <hi>Croeſus</hi> ſent to the ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of <hi>Delphos:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Herod. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Croeſus</hi> ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for him and offered him aſmuch gold as at one time he could beare out of his treaſure houſe. <hi>Alcmaeon</hi> not a little glad of the offer, prepared a large doublet with wide fleeues, a paire of breeches reaching downe to his heeles, both of them fitter for <hi>Hercules</hi> then for himſelfe. This done he went to <hi>Croeſus</hi> his coffers, &amp; firſt fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his breeches as full as hee could ſtuffe them, then his ſleeues, and boſome, then glued as much as hee could to the haires
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:25300:15"/> of his head, and beard, &amp; then laſtly ſtuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed his mouth with as much as hee could thruſt in it, and ſo with much adoe, crept out of the treaſure houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lication to magiſtrats</note>This ſinne, as of all men it is to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided, ſo eſpecially of magiſtrats which ſit at the ſterne to direct our ſhip in this <hi>glaſſie</hi> ſea: and which are the pillars of iuſtice to ſupport her battered fabricke. Yee muſt not giue it the leaſt welcome in your hearts: but (like the wiſe travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler) ſtoppe your eares at the ſongs of this Syren, and not giue it the leaſt attention though it charme never ſo cunningly. You ſhould haue eies like vnto <hi>Lynceus,</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iue into the bottom of the moſt deep and abſtruſe controverſies. Now <hi>hope of reward blindeth the eies of the wiſe:</hi> ſo that as a blind man which hath a pearle vpon his eies, cannot ſee his way, but ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth at every blocke, and falleth head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into every pit: right ſo if you ſhall haue this rich pearle (this pearle of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches) before your eies, you can never tread right in the way of truth. The eie, or any facultie of the ſenſuall, or in elle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall part, if it bee buſied about any one obiect neglecteth the reſt: &amp; if your eies
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:25300:15"/> bee exerciſed about this obiect, it will make you negligent in publike affaires.<note place="margin">Ariſt. de ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma lib <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Intùs apparens prohibet alienum:</hi> if the <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> of gold poſſeſſe your heartes, there will be no roome for iuſtice to lodge in them. For theſe two bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>non benè conveniunt nec in vnâ ſede mora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur.</hi> They ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no more lodge within the ſame breaſt then light with darkneſſe, the arke with <hi>Dagon,</hi> God with <hi>Mammon.</hi> It was <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars</hi> ſaying, borrowed from <hi>Euripides</hi> in his <hi>Phoeniſſa: If iuſtice muſt be broken,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cic. lib. <hi>3.</hi> Offic.</note> 
               <hi>it muſt be for raigning.</hi> But hee might more truely haue ſaid, <hi>for gaining.</hi> For gold could never away with iuſtice, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Poets faine, that when gold firſt began to be digged out of the earth, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice durſt tary no longer, but preſently fled into heaven.<note place="margin">Exod. 18.21</note> Therefore <hi>Iethro</hi> deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the qual<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tie of a good iudge, ſaith that he muſt deale iuſtly or <hi>truely,</hi> &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he addes, as it were by way of explicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the better vnderſtanding of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer word, that he <hi>muſt hate covetouſnes:</hi> as if he had ſaid, if he be a covetous, and gold-thirſting man he cannot bee a true and iuſt dealer. And to this purpoſe <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> prayeth, Pſ. 119. that <hi>the Lord would
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:25300:16"/> encline his heart to his t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtimonies, &amp; not to covetouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> To lawyers</note>7 Now as this inſatiable deſire of gain, is not to ſit on the bench with the iudge, ſo is it not to plead at the bar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e with the counſellor, which with the key of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is to vnlock the ſecrets of the law, and with a skilfull, &amp; expert hand, to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie the knots of hard and difficult queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. It will make him Phariſee-like to ſtraine a Gnat, and to ſwallow a Camell; to tythe mint, and cummin, &amp; to let paſſe iudgement and fidelity, it will make his tongue play faſt and looſe with iuſtice at its pleaſure. A golden key commonly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens a wrong locke. <hi>Auro loquente, nihil pollet quaevis oratio.</hi> When <hi>Pluto</hi> ſpeaks <hi>Plato</hi> may holde his hande on his mouth like <hi>Harpocrates</hi> the <hi>Egyptian</hi> God, &amp; ſay nothing. It is a great come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation which <hi>Tullie</hi> giues vnto a Lawyer:<note place="margin">De orat. l. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The mouth of a Lawyer is an oracle for the whole citie.</hi> But if this mouth bee once corrupted with gold it will proue like the oracle of <hi>Delphos,</hi> of which <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his time,<note place="margin">Tull. de di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinat. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> that it did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſpeake nothing but what <hi>Philip,</hi> which gaue it a double fee would haue it to ſay.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:25300:16"/> And ſuch an oracle <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> himſelfe ſometime proved:<note place="margin">Aul. Gel. l. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> cap <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> who being feed to plead a cauſe, &amp; immediatly after recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a large ſumme of mony of the other party for holding his peace, the next day comes into the court in a rug-gowne, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his necke, &amp; iawes all muffled with furres, and warme cloathes, and told the iudges he was troubled with a <hi>ſquinancie</hi> that he could not ſpeake. Whervpon one that perceived his diſeaſe, ſaid that it was not a colde, but gold that hindered his ſpeech. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an Oxe, I warrant you, was in his tongue. The <hi>Athenian</hi> coine which was ſtamped with the form of an Oxe had bunged vp his mouth, no marvaile if he was ſpeechleſſe.</p>
            <p n="8">8 But eſpecially this ſin is to bee avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of you that are witneſſes, and iurers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> To wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and Iurers,</note> which are the one by teſtifying the other by examining the trueth to make a finall deciſion of controverſies. If you ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine any ſuch thought as to ſaie with <hi>Iudas, What will yee giue me?</hi> yee ſhall be ſure to finde ſome <hi>Simon Magus</hi> ready to ſay? <hi>What ſhall I giue you?</hi> Falſity and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing haue ever bin the handmaides to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe. And therfore when the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:25300:17"/> 
               <hi>Ieremie</hi> complaineth, <hi>that from the leaſt to the greatest they were al give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 6.13.</note> it muſt needs be true which he addeth in the next words, <hi>that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the Prieſt they all dealt falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> As <hi>Iudas</hi> was hereby moved to betray his maſter, ſo were the ſouldiers perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to lie, and falſely to forſweare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that his diſciples ſtole him awaie when they were aſleepe; and that moſt palpably too. For if they were aſleepe how knew they that it was his diſciples, and if they knew that it was his diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iples, how were they aſleepe?</p>
            <p n="9">
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.15</note>9 Follow not then <hi>the waies of Balaam the ſonne of Boſor which loued the wages of vnrighteouſnes.</hi> Only herein ye muſt keep his reſolution,<note place="margin">Num. 24.13</note> 
               <hi>not for an houſe full of ſilver and gold to goe beyond the worde of truth to ſay leſſe or more.</hi> Equivocations and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall reſervations which the Papiſts make ſuch reckoning off, are the ready waie to renew that old <hi>tohu,</hi> and <hi>bohu,</hi> to make a <hi>chaos</hi> and confuſion of all things,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> to mixe light and darknes, truth &amp; falſhood, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and hell togither. Whoſoever ſhal for filthy lucre ſake, either wittingly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale part of the truth, or adde any thing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:25300:17"/> thereto, and thereby turne the truth into a ly,<note place="margin">Eccl 6.3.</note> I ſay vnto you that an vntimely <hi>birth is better then hee.</hi> And better it were for him vnleſſe he repent,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.6.</note> 
               <hi>that a milſtone were put about his necke, and that he were drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the deepe of the ſea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 To end this point,<note place="margin">4 <hi>To all.</hi> Luk 12.13. Eph. 5.3.</note> let me ſpeake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you al in the words of our Saviour, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of covetouſnes,</hi> &amp; with the Apoſtle, <hi>let it not be once named amongſt you.</hi> But if ye wil needs be covetous,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>covet spirituall things:</hi> ſet not your <hi>heartes on the things that are below, but on the thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s that are aboue.</hi> Covet that which wil ſatiate your hearts, and that is nothing in this world. For the hart is triangular, and the world is round, and a round body cannot fill a triangle, but there will remaine ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me emptie corners: no more can the whole world fill the three corners of an heart, nor any thing ſaue he which is three, and one, God bleſſed for evermore. <hi>Inquietu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt cor noſtrum O Deus poſtquam receſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus à te donec revertamur ad te,</hi> ſaith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> O God our heart is never contented when we turne from thee, till we returne to thee. Oh then as your hearts are, ſo let your hearts deſire bee; that is, the <hi>Baſis</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:25300:18"/> or broader part vpward toward heaven, and heavenly things, &amp; the <hi>conus</hi> or nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row point towardes earth and earthly things. Vſe not your riches as <hi>Anachar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> ſaid the <hi>Athenians</hi> did their money: <hi>Nummis ad numerandum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. de pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect virt. ſent.</note> onely to count it over, &amp; then to coffer it vp. Inioy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ioy not immoderatly in them, know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing this that yee are not owners, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſers of the things that yee poſſeſſe. Alas why ſhould a man, which is a little world of himſelfe, a man whoſe conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation ſhould be in heaven, bee wedded to theſe baſe, and vile excrements of the earth? they deſerue no better name. For what I pray you is the beſt gold, but a congealed vapour? and the greateſt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions but ſo much earth? and the fineſt ſilke, but excrements of ſillie wormes, which liue but two or three months? <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> had as much experience in them as any man that ever lived.<note place="margin">1. Kings. 10 17.</note> For <hi>hee gaue in Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſilver as ſtones, &amp; Cedar trees, as the wild fig-trees that grow abundantly in the plaines,</hi> yet in his old age, when hee became a preacher, and repented him of his former life, he tooke ſuch ſmall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in this tranſitory traſh, that in the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:25300:18"/> beginning of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> hee tooke this for his text, <hi>Vanitie of vanities,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>and all is but vaniti:</hi> and if they be weighed in the balance of the Sanctuary, they wil want of weight. <hi>They are altogether vanitie, nay they are lighter then vanitie it ſelfe.</hi> Let vs then ſo loue them, as that we care not to leaue them: and in all things,<note place="margin">Plilip. 4.12</note> 
               <hi>let vs learne both to be hungry, and to bee full, and to abound, and to haue want:</hi> accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all things, but <hi>loſſe,</hi> and <hi>droſſe, and dung, that wee may winne Chriſt.</hi> Which <hi>Iudas</hi> for the deſire of a little mony pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth to deliver vnto the high Prieſt: <hi>I will deliver him vnto you.</hi> And ſo I come to the particulars of the ſecond generall branch of my text.</p>
            <p n="11">11 And firſt wee are to begin with the <hi>Perſon</hi> delivering, and that is <hi>Iudas,</hi> no <hi>Saducee,</hi> nor <hi>Phariſee</hi> which oppugned his doctrine, no profeſſed enimie which openly ſought his deſtruction, but an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, one of the twelue which hee had choſen vnto himſelfe, and ſent abroad to preach the Goſpell, and to caſt out Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, and to heale the ſicke. Hence I infer this concluſion: <hi>that no calling is ſo holy but that it hath ſome wicked impes, &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:25300:19"/> hypocrites (which though for a space they may deceaue the world with a vizard of holineſſe, yet time will vnmaske and ſhew them in their owne colours) inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixed with true profeſſors.</hi> A concluſion which if the inſtances of our time could not make good, the premiſes of all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages do abundantly demonſtrate it. When as yet our firſt parents had no mo children then <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen 4.</note> the elder of theſe two, the firſt that ever was borne of a woman, the heire apparent of the whole world, was an Apoſtata: his hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie was diſcloſed in killing his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. When the whole Church was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinged within the ſides of one arke, all were not ſheepe that were in this little fold,<note place="margin">Gen. 7.</note> for —<hi>Nat lupus inter oves,</hi> there ſwamme one wolfe among theſe ſheepe. As there was a <hi>Sem</hi> which was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected; ſo was there a <hi>Cham</hi> which was reiected: his apoſtaſie declared in mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his father. Of the ſame father (even of him,<note place="margin">Gen. 16.</note> 
               <hi>who was the father of the faithfull</hi>) there came an <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> as wel as an <hi>Iſaac;</hi> of the ſame mother (even at one and the ſelfe ſame birth) came an <hi>Eſau,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 4 16.</note> as well as a <hi>Iacob.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 25.24</note> The ſame kingdome had as well
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:25300:19"/> a <hi>Saul,</hi> as a <hi>David:</hi> the ſame place a <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabas,</hi> and a <hi>Barnabas,</hi> the ſame profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a <hi>Cephas,</hi> and a <hi>Caiphas,</hi> a <hi>Iude,</hi> &amp; a <hi>Iuda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> and as it was, ſo it ſhall ever bee till the ſonne of man come in the glory of his kingdome, as longe as the nett ſwims in the ſalt ſea of this world, till it bee brought to land, it ſhall containe both good &amp; bad fiſhes. Till the reapers come there muſt growe wheat and tares toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this field: till the ſhepheard come there muſt bee ſheepe and goates in this fold.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.20.</note> This great houſe till it be builded a new, muſt containe <hi>veſſels of honour, and veſſels of diſhonour:</hi> the gold muſt be mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the droſſe, till the great and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible fire come to ſeparate them. In this floore the wheat ſhall bee mingled with the chaffe, till the Lord <hi>come with his fan in his hand</hi> to winnow it, and ſhall blow the chaffe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.</note> and ſcatter it <hi>away from the face of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
               </label> The reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s here of firſt reſpect the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, &amp; that is to make them more inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable, in that converſing with the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>they doe not learn godlines:</hi> but as thoſe which walke in the ſunne, though they change their outward colour, yet they
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:25300:20"/> ſtil retaine their inward nature, ſo theſe though they receiue an outward tincture of godlines, yet they ſtil keepe their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward corruption. Herevpon it is that <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>razin</hi> and <hi>Bethſaida</hi> are more inexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.21. Mat. 12 41.</note> then <hi>Tyrus</hi> and <hi>Sidon:</hi> that <hi>the men of Niniue, &amp; the Queene of the South ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe againſt the Iewes and ſhall condemne them:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11.23</note> that <hi>it ſhall be better for them of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the day of iudgment, then for Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The lord by this meanes effecteth the converſion of ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, which are not yet cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. For as the <hi>Aramits,</hi> by walking with the Prophet,<note place="margin">2. King. 6.</note> were at vnawares brought to <hi>Samaria:</hi> ſo many who are not as yet called by walking with the righteous, are catched at vnawares, and brought to Chriſts ſheepfold.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The lord doth hereby exerciſe his children and keepes them ſtill fighting, wheras otherwiſe they would be readie to fall a ſleepe in the cradle of carnall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie. The coldnes of devotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is in the worldlings, doth by an <hi>Antiperiſtaſis</hi> ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times ſtir vp the heat of zeal in Gods children. While the wind ſtriues to blow out the fire it encreaſeth the flame, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:25300:20"/> while the wicked doe indeavour to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the heat of zeale in Gods children, and to make them as cold as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are, they often blow it vp, &amp; make it farre greater then it was before.</p>
            <p>I told you before what <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith of <hi>Muraena,</hi> that his chaſtity was more ſeen in living amongſt the effeminate <hi>Aſians,</hi> then ever it was at <hi>Rome.</hi> And I am ſure <hi>Lots</hi> continencie did farre more appeare when hee lived amongſt the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> then when he was in the mountain with his two daughters.<note place="margin">Gen. 19.</note> If Gods children ſhould haue none but ſuch as <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> to converſe with them, they would ſay as <hi>Peter</hi> did vnto Chriſt, when hee was transfigured vpon the mountaine, <hi>Maſter it is good for vs to be here:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 9.5.</note> 
               <hi>let vs here</hi> (vpon this mountaine) <hi>build vs ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles.</hi> They would never ſay with the Pſalmiſt:<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.8.</note> 
               <hi>Lord who ſhall dwell in thy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, and who ſhall reſt vpon thy moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine?</hi> Whereas now being vexed with theſe <hi>Cananites</hi> that dwell amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>and are thornes in their ſides,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 33.59.</note> 
               <hi>and pricks in their eies:</hi> they are wearie of the earthly <hi>Canaan,</hi> &amp; long for another, which flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with better things then milke &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:25300:21"/> They cry out as <hi>Rebecca</hi> when ſhee felt the two twinnes ſtruggling in her wombe:<note place="margin">Gen. 25 22</note> 
               <hi>if it be ſo, why are we thus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> 12 To leaue then the concluſion, and to come to ſome application therof. Are the wicked intermixed with true &amp; zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous profeſſours? What ſhall we then ſay to the old <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> and the <hi>Browniſts,</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> which ſeparate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from the true Church, &amp; ſay with thoſe in the Prophet, <hi>Come not neere vs for we are holier then ye?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Socrat. hiſt. Eccleſ. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> Me thinks I may ſay vnto them as <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ſaid to <hi>Ace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> a <hi>Novatian</hi> Biſhop: Let them make a ladder for themſelues to aſcend into heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, here is no place for them on earth, as long as this world ſhall laſt, the Lords wheate ſhall growe vp with the tares. Chriſt hath ſpoken it,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.29.</note> and Chriſt is truth, <hi>if there bee in them any charitie, they will aſſent to this veritie:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sit in illis charitas &amp; congaudeant vernate Aug. <hi>Cor. 2.6.</hi>
               </note> yea but light hath no communion with darkneſſe, nor bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe with honie, nor life with death, nor the vnbeleeuer with the infidell. It is the obiection of <hi>Petilian</hi> the <hi>Donatiſt</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Auſtin.</hi> But his anſwer is, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they eſchew the darkneſſe, they forſake the light: when they flee from death they
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:25300:21"/> flee from life alſo. <hi>Attendis Zizania per mundum, &amp; triticum non attendis, cum per totum vtra<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſint iuſſa creſcere? atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis ſemen maligni, quod ad finem meſſis ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parabitur; &amp; non attendis ſemen Abrahae, in quo benedicentur omnes gentes?</hi> Doſt thou marke the darnell, &amp; doſt thou not remember the wheat? Doſt thou thinke vpon the ſeed of the ſerpent, whoſe head ſhall be cruſhed; and doſt thou not think vpon the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> in whom all the nations of the earth ſhall be bleſſed? when thou fleeſt from the chaffe, thou forſakeſt the good wheat, which is min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with it. When thou ſeparateſt thy ſelfe from the ſeed of the wicked, thou ſeperateſt thy ſelfe from the ſeede of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham.</hi> When thou thus divideſt thy ſelfe from the hypocrits, that are in the true Church, thou cutteſt thy ſelfe from the Church, and a member taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whole muſt needs periſh. If thou wilt thinke vpon this with that heedfulneſſe that thou ſhouldſt, thou wilt not forſake the greene paſtures of the Lord, that <hi>are beſides the waters of comfort,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 3.</note> becauſe of the <hi>goats;</hi> nor leaue Gods <hi>houſe,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>veſſels of diſhonour;</hi> nor runne out
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:25300:22"/> of the Lords <hi>floore,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>chaffe;</hi> nor ſeparate thy ſelfe from the <hi>wheat,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the <hi>tares,</hi> which ſhall at length be <hi>bound in a bundle, and caſt into the fire;</hi> nor burſt the vnitie of the Lords <hi>net,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the <hi>bad fiſh,</hi> which ſwimme in it, (which, when the net is brought to land, ſhal be caſt away:) but as a Father ſpeaks <hi>tolerare potiùs propter bonos co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mixtionem malorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug lib. <hi>3.</hi> contra litt. Petit. cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quàm violare propter malos cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem bonorum;</hi> rather for the good to tolerate the bad, then for the bad to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the good.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> But before I leaue this point, I muſt giue thee this leſſon (and I beſeech thee marke it well) though of neceſſitie thou muſt liue amongſt the vngodly,<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.12.</note> yet <hi>thou muſt not walke in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell of the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> much leſſe <hi>ſtand in the way of ſinners,</hi> &amp; leaſt of all, <hi>ſit down in the ſeat of the ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi> Though thou dwell among wolues, thou muſt not <hi>vlulare cum lupis,</hi> howle with the wolues:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.10</note> though thou accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with the <hi>fornicators of this world,</hi> and with the <hi>covetous, and with extortio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, &amp; with Idolaters, (for elſe thou muſt goe out of this world)</hi> yet be not partaker with them in their ſinnes, leaſt thou bee
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:25300:22"/> partaker with them in their puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. Though a corporall ſeparation cannot bee had, yet in ſpirit thou muſt ſeparate thy ſelfe:<note place="margin">2. Tim 2.19</note> 
               <hi>for let every one that calleth on the name of the Lord, ſeparate himſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iniquitie.</hi> Thou ſeeſt what is thy lot, if not with <hi>Lot,</hi> to dwell with <hi>Sodomites:</hi> or with <hi>Naaman,</hi> to be amongſt the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites:</hi> or with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to liue amongſt the <hi>Egyptians;</hi> if thou canſt not ſay with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 120.5.</note> 
               <hi>Woe is mee that I am conſtrained to dwell in Meſhech, and to haue mine abode in the tents of Kedar:</hi> Yet maiſt thou ſay with <hi>Eſay, Woe is mee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 6.5.</note> 
               <hi>for I dwell in the midſt of a people of polluted lippes.</hi> With Chriſt and his Apoſtles, thou muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with a <hi>Iudas:</hi> with the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> thou muſt liue with the <hi>Cananites:</hi> with the Spouſe in the Canticles, thou muſt bee as <hi>an apple tree amongſt the wild trees of the forreſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 2.2, 3</note> or as <hi>a lilie amongſt the thornes.</hi> Let not theſe wild trees, which are moued with every blaſt of winde, by the ſhaking of their boughs beat downe thy fruit, and though the thornes pricke thee, yet keepe ſtill a lilies beautie. Thou muſt touch pitch, but beware of being defiled with it. Thou muſt walke vpon
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:25300:23"/> coales, beware of burning thy feete: though thou lie among the pots, among the waſhpots of the Lord (as<note n="o" place="margin">Pſ 108.9.</note> 
               <hi>Moab</hi> is called) amongſt the veſſels of diſhonour that are kept for the day of wrath, yet muſt thou be as the <hi>wings of a doue, that is covered with ſilver wings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 67.13.</note> 
               <hi>and her fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers like gold.</hi> Be not like the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that carieth the ſmel of his ſhop a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with him, nor like the river <hi>Iordan,</hi> which<note n="q" place="margin">Plin. nat. hiſt. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>15</hi>
               </note> looſeth his ſweet waters in the lake <hi>Aſphaltites.</hi> But like the fiſh in the ſalt ſea, which ſtill retaine their freſhnes; paſſe through the briniſh Ocean of this world, as <hi>Arethuſa</hi> doth vnder the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilian ſea,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Virg. Eclog. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Doris amara ſuam non intermiſceat vnda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> In a word, though thou canſt not wholy ſeparate thy ſelfe from the workers of darkneſſe, yet <hi>haue no fellowſhip with the vnfruitfull workes of darkneſſe, but even reproue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rather.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.11.</note> Nay from ſuch works, as much as thou maiſt lawfully, ſeparate thy ſelfe: for thou wilt in time ioy in the latter, if thou long enioy the former, it is a matter of ſome difficultie to bee conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually handling pitch, and birdlime, and to haue none cleaue to thy hands.<note n="a" place="margin">Ariſt. Met. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:25300:23"/> noteth it of his maſter <hi>Plato,</hi> that converſing long with the <hi>Pythagorians,</hi> hee learned from them many erronious opinions, which afterward he ſtifly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.<note n="b" place="margin">Q. Cur.</note> 
               <hi>Alexander</hi> by converſing with the effeminate <hi>Perſians,</hi> and<note n="c" place="margin">Liv. dec. <hi>3.</hi> lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Annibal</hi> by liuing in <hi>Capua,</hi> did abate ſo much of their former valour, that it was doubted whether they were the ſame me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had beene before.<note n="d" place="margin">Sozom. l. cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iulian,</hi> in profeſſion ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a Chriſtian, by converſing with <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>banius,</hi> and <hi>Maximus,</hi> became an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtata. To goe no further with the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of heathen men, you knowe that <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> living in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court, began to ſweare<note n="e" place="margin">Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 42.1.</note> by the life of <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> And the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> dwelling among the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous <hi>Egyptians</hi> (which<note n="f" place="margin">Herod. l.</note> worſhipped an oxe) did meetly well imitate them, for they<note n="g" place="margin">Exod. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> worſhipped a calfe. And pitching for a time in the plane of <hi>Moab, they ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed to Baal Peor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 25 Pſ. 106.26</note> 
               <hi>and ate the offerings of the dead.</hi> An infected ſheepe will ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſpoile a whole flocke, then a whole flocke will cure an infected ſheepe. It is no hard matter to change wine into vineger, but to turn vineger, onto cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge water into wine,
<q>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:25300:24"/>Hoc opus, hic labor eſt.</q> This is ſuch a miracle as will never bee wrought, vnleſſe <hi>Ieſus</hi> be at the feaſt. It is an eaſie matter to bee infected with the plague of ſin, if thou remoue out of the freſh aire into the company of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tagious perſons. And though thou be regenerate, &amp; the old ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath got his deadly wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, yet is there a ſympathy betweene thee, &amp; the wicked. Thy affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are like tindar, ready to kindle with every ſparkle, that the wicked ſhal ſtrike in them. And ſinne once kindled is like wilde fire, it will not be quenched with every kinde of water. This poiſon perhaps wil not be perceived at the firſt, yet, like the biting of a madde dogge, it will never ceaſe infecting thy blood till it come at thy hart. <hi>Beware</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>of dogs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philip. 3.2.</note> Avoid (as much as is poſſible) ſuch contagious places, as are dangerous to infect, and keepe thy ſelfe in the freſh aire, where the ſpirit, that quickneth, doth blow. But whereas thou canſt not wholly avoid the company of ſinners (for as before was ſaid, the good and bad fiſh ſwim togither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Gods net) avoid their ſinnes.<note place="margin">Prov. 1.10.11.</note> Harken vnto <hi>Solomon, My ſonne, if ſinners entice thee, conſent thou not. My
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:25300:24"/> ſonne, walke not thou in the way with them, refraine thy foot from their path;</hi> but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywiſe when they entice thee to evill, perſwade them vnto that which is good. Be to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as <hi>Noah</hi> was to the old world, <hi>a preacher of righteouſneſſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Verſ. 8.</note> as <hi>Lot</hi> was to the <hi>Sodomites, who dwelling amongſt them vexed his ſoule with their vnlawfull deeds;</hi> as Chriſt was to the woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh 4.</note> who by deſiring of the water of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> well to quench his thirſt, brought her to deſire the water of life, <hi>wherof who ſoever drinketh ſhall never more thirſt;</hi> and as he was with Publicanes and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, who refuſed not to goe to their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall banquets, that he might feed them with ſpirituall foode; as <hi>Iohn</hi> was with the <hi>Phariſees</hi> &amp; <hi>Saducees,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 3.</note> who preached vnto them faith and repentance; and as <hi>Paul</hi> was amongſt the idolatrous <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> who went with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, through their idolatrous temples, and red the titles and inſcriptions written vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their altars, but to this end, to take a text, and argument thence,<note place="margin">Act. 17.23.</note> to perſwade them to the worſhip of the true God.</p>
            <p>So much of the perſon delivering. The action followeth, <hi>(deliver.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:25300:25"/>
               <note place="margin">Deliver.]</note>13 Treaſon is a ſinne ſo odious, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the heathen which were guided, but with a glimpſe of natures light, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſometimes for their own advantage, they approved the fact, yet they coulde never away with the author of it. It was <hi>Auguſtus</hi> his ſaying of <hi>Rimotalchus</hi> the king of <hi>Trace,</hi> which vanted himſelfe for the betraying of <hi>Antonie:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>I may loue the treaſon but I hate the traitour.</hi> And it was the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Antigonus: Proditores tantisper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo dum produnt, aſt vbi prodiderint odi.</hi> I loue a traitour whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mits the treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but when he hath done it, I deteſt him. Theſe ſpeeches, though plauſible at the firſt, argue corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſpeakers. For if the traitour be evill, ſurely the treaſon cannot be good. The old <hi>Romanes</hi> could abide neither. For when <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> his phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſeeking to gratifie the <hi>Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to giue his maſter poiſon, the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes</hi> made <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> acquainted with it, &amp; willed him to look vnto himſelfe. And when the ſchoolemaſter of the <hi>Phalaſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> offered to betray thoſe which were committed to him,<note place="margin">Liv. dec. <hi>1.</hi> lib. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> to <hi>Camillus</hi> his hand: <hi>Camillus</hi> ſent them backe againe,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:25300:25"/> and made his own ſchollers to beat him.</p>
            <p>This fact, of it ſelfe ſo hainous,<note place="margin">Him.</note> is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aggravated by the perſon betrayed. If <hi>Iudas</hi> had betrayed one of his fellows, the ſin had bin horrible: but he makes it farre worſe, he betrayeth his maſter. He goes yet further, for (behold whither ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth fal,<note place="margin">Vnto you. Luk. <hi>1.71.</hi>
               </note> if the ſpirit of God do not direct his ſteps) he delivereth him into the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of his hatefull enimies, <hi>who came to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver vs from our enimies and from the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of all that hate vs.</hi> He delivereth him to death, who came to reſtore vs, that were dead in our ſinnes, to life; who to ſatisfie for our hunting after vanities, was him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hunted like a <hi>Pelican in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> to ſatisfie for our carnall, and ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all pleaſures, left the boſome of his father with whom is fulneſſe of delights, and at whoſe right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is pleaſure forevermore: to ſatisfie for our pride, humbled himſelf and <hi>tooke vpon him the forme of a ſervant:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.7.</note> to anſwere for our gluttony, taſted gall, and vineger; to anſwer for our covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, paid not gold, nor ſilver, but the ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of his owne blood. Theſe things I do but point at, having diſcourſed of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> elſewhere, when I handled our Saviours
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:25300:26"/> milde ſpeech vnto <hi>Iudas,</hi> when he went to betray him. Therefore I paſſe them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, &amp; come to apply this fact vnto theſe preſent times.</p>
            <p n="14">14 <hi>Iudas</hi> is dead, and al men cry, fie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and ſay that it if they had bin in <hi>Iudas</hi> his daies, they would not haue bin partners with him in the blood of our Saviour. And ſo ſaid the old <hi>Phariſees,</hi> if they had bin in the daies of their fathers, they would not haue bin partners with them in the blood of the Prophets.<note place="margin">Mat. 23.30.</note> And yet they fulfilled, nay they exceeded the meaſure of their fathers wickednes. And now adaies howſoever many will build the tombes of the Prophets, and garniſh the ſepulchers of the righteous, yet wee haue <hi>Iudaſſes,</hi> which wil betray <hi>Chriſt</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the high Prieſts. I cannot recke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al, but there are 3. <hi>tranſgreſſors,</hi> nay 4. which I cannot paſſe over. 1. the <hi>ſacrilegious Churchrobber,</hi> 2. the <hi>grinding oppreſſor.</hi> 3. <hi>the cloſe briber.</hi> 4. the <hi>deceitfull lawyer.</hi> Al theſe do their beſt (nay their worſt) to be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tray Chriſt, if not in his perſon, yet in his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, into the hands of the helliſh <hi>Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas.</hi> And me thinks they do ſomwhat re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble thoſe 4. great plagues mentioned in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:25300:26"/> the 1. of <hi>Ioel:</hi> which were: the Caterpiller, the Locuſt, the Cankerworme &amp; the graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hopper. The Caterpiller eats the firſt fruits when they are in ſetting. To him I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the Church-robber, which liues of the firſt fruits &amp; tithes, which by the law are due to God. The Locuſt (as Natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts deſcribe him) is a great flie, which li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth vpon the leſſe, and with no difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty can burſt a ſpiders webbe, wherein the ſmaller flies are quickly catched. To him I compare the oppreſſour, which devours his inferiours, and will with no leſſe diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty paſſe through thoſe good ſtatutes that are made againſt him, then a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eat Locuſt will burſt through a ſpiders web. The Canker-worme doth ſecretly ſhaue off the tender barks of hearbs &amp; trees be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he can be perceived. To him may be likened the briber, which doth ſo cloſely cary himſelfe, that none ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perceiue him, but the plant which he feeds vpon. The Graſhopper hath a chirping voice to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure a man after him, but yet ſo nimble is his motion, that he which followeth him ſhall ſcarſely finde him. Like to it, is the deceitfull lawyer, which with faire pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and ſugered hopes, draws his cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:25300:27"/> after him; but ſo nimbly hee hops vp and downe, for his owne advantage, that ye ſhall perhaps not finde him twiſe in one tune, inſomuch that ye ſhal be worſe reſolved in the end, then ye were in the beginning. Theſe 4. lie as heavy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our land, as thoſe 4. plagues did vpon <hi>Iudah:</hi> ſo that wee may ſay, <hi>that which is left by the Locuſt, the graſhopper hath eaten, and the reſidue of the graſhopper, hath the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerworme eaten, and the reſidue of the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerworme hath the caterpiller eaten.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I begin to ſpeake of theſe in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, let me vſe the Apoſtles proteſtation. <hi>I ſay the truth in Chriſt Ieſus, I ly not, my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience bearing me witnes in the holy ghoſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9.1.</note> I do not ſeeke the diſgrace of any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, it is the truths cauſe, and Gods cauſe that moveth me to ſpeake (and let my tongue cleaue to the roofe of my mouth when I ſhal be afraid to diſcharge a good conſcience in Gods behalfe.) If then my muſicke ſeeme harſh, &amp; vnplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in the eares of any that heare me, I would haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to know thus much, that the ſtrings vpon which a I am to play are farre out of tune. If any man ſhall finde himſelfe wounded with my ſpeech, I ſay
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:25300:27"/> vnto him as our Saviour did to the adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſe, <hi>Hath no man condemned thee? nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I condemne thee;</hi> yet I adde with <hi>Iohn, if thine owne heart do condemne thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.10.11. 1. Ioh. 3.20</note> 
               <hi>God is greater then thy heart and knoweth all things,</hi> &amp; therfore I diſmiſſe thee with that ſpeach of Chriſt to the impotent ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>go thy way, and ſinne no more,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.14.</note> 
               <hi>leaſt a worſe thing happen vnto thee.</hi> Now to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <p n="15">15 In the firſt place come the <hi>Simoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acall patrons,</hi> the heires and eldeſt ſons of <hi>Iudas,</hi> the <hi>caterpillers</hi> of our church, &amp; the notableſt theeues in all our lande. Which will not part with that portion which is due vnto the ſons of <hi>Levi,</hi> and which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted vnto them, as the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den apple was vnto <hi>Paris,</hi> with this mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ingraven vpon it, <hi>detur digniori,</hi> let the moſt worthy haue it, vnleſſe with <hi>Iudas</hi> they covena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for a price before hand. Let a mans gifts of minde bee never ſo good, yet if he bring no gifts in hand; let his care, and induſtry, and learning be never ſo rare, &amp; extraordinary, yet if he do not ſpeake with the tongue of men, &amp; <hi>angels</hi> yea <hi>arke-angels,</hi> he ſhall haue little hope to prevaile in his ſuit. He that wil inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:25300:28"/> himſelfe into their favors, muſt come, as <hi>Iupiter</hi> came into <hi>Danaes lap, per im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pluvium,</hi> ſecretly in at the chimney top, (not in at the dore) and he muſt come as <hi>Iupiter</hi> then came, <hi>in a ſhower of gold.</hi> This is the way, this is the beſt meanes to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect his deſire: for he that is as blockiſh and ſtupid,<note place="margin">Plut. Apoth.</note> as <hi>Philips Aſſe in Plutarch,</hi> if he bee loaden with gold (with that aſſe) oh he is a man of excellent gifts, of rare endowments, no exception muſt keepe him backe; that which hee wants in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, he hath it in ſimplicity: as if it were <hi>ſimplicitas Aſinina,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10.16.</note> &amp; not <hi>ſimplicitas co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbina,</hi> which the Lord would haue in his miniſters. And what if he lacke La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine? he hath <hi>gold</hi> enough, &amp; that is a far more pretious mettal. But if this way wil not hold, then they will take another courſe, they will act the parts of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> &amp; keepe backe part of that poſſeſſion, which they ſhould voluntari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>lay downe at the Apoſtles feete.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 4.12.</note> There muſt be an exception in the general rule, a reſervation of their owne tithes, a limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch a towneſhip, or ſuch a field. Or they will ſay with the harlot, 1. Kin. 3 <hi>Let it neither bee thine nor mine, but let it be
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:25300:28"/> divided.</hi> Here is treaſon in another kind; they doe not ſell the king of heauen, by covenanting for a price before hand, as <hi>Iudas</hi> did, but (which is all to one effect) they clip his coine and make it ſo light, that it will not ſuſtaine the ſonnes of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi.</hi> And this verily is a principall reaſon, that we haue ſo many <hi>mutes,</hi> and ſo fewe <hi>vowels</hi> in our croſſe rowe: that many lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wings which hopped out of their neaſts with their ſhels on their heads, before e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they get a feather on their backes, haue builded in thoſe rocks where eagls ſhould neſtle; and many which haue ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver put downe their buckets, into either of the two fountaines of this land (or if they haue, it hath beene but <hi>tanquam ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ad Nilum,</hi> they haue onely wet their lips, and taken a lappe by the way) are advanced to Eccleſiaſticall preferments, and made Paſtors of flocks being not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to feed themſelues, and are become captaines in the Lords field, being not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of themſelues to take one ſtone out of Gods brooke to caſt at the forehead of the ſpirituall <hi>Goliah.</hi> I confeſſe ſome of them will now and then be flinging in the pulpit, but they be <hi>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tita tela,</hi> other
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:25300:29"/> mens weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s they fight with: they haue, indeed, as good a propertie in them, as they haue in their benefices, and as <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> in <hi>Martial</hi> had in his verſes,<note place="margin">Carmina Paulus emit, iactat ſua carmina Paulus: nam, quod emit, poſſit dicere iure ſuum. <hi>Iudg. 18.</hi>
               </note> which he vſed to bragge off. Such wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dring <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites</hi> as theſe are the fitteſt marchants that ſacrilegious <hi>Iudaſſes</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: for they will bee contented to dwell with every baſe filching <hi>Michah:</hi> &amp; will ſerue him for <hi>ten ſhekles of ſilver by the yeare, and a ſuit of apparell, and meate, and drinke,</hi> and withall their hearts, will bee contented to part with beautifull <hi>Rahel,</hi> (though they ſerue for her) ſo that they may be aſſured of blear-eyed <hi>Leah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 29.</note> They will never ſay as much as <hi>Iacob</hi> did to <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ban: Wherefore hast thou done thus with me? did I not ſerue thee for Rahel? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then haſt thou beguiled me?</hi> Truth it is, that even theſe would gladly mend their eſtates (and who can blame them?) but they are withholden with a triple cord, which, as the wiſe man ſaith, <hi>is not eaſily broken.</hi> 1. The Patrons bountie, which though it bee little, yet it is more perhaps then they deſerue. 2. Their owne promiſe, or hand writing, which if it bee not of ſufficient validitie, then comes a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:25300:29"/> third cord to make all ſure, and that is want of abilitie. A ſpiders webbe (you knowe) is ſtrong enough to hang a ſillie flie withal. God forbid that I ſhould ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect this ſacrilege, as a generall fault of theſe times, not admitting any limitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; or ſay that theſe devouring <hi>Caterpillers haue eaten vp all the houſes of God in the land.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 19.</note> I remember what the Lord anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Elias,</hi> when hee complained againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that they had killed his Prophets, and digged downe his altars, and that he was left alone.<note place="margin">Ro. 11.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>I haue</hi> (ſaid the anſwer of God) <hi>reſerved vnto my ſelfe ſeaven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, which haue not bowed their knees vnto Baal.</hi> Even ſo, at this preſent time, by the grace of God, there is a remnant (though I thinke farre fewer then ſeaven thouſand) yet a remnant there is, which haue never digged downe the altars of God to build their own houſes with the ruines thereof; which haue not bowed <hi>vnto their angle, nor ſacrificed vnto their net, nor burnt incenſe vnto their yarne,</hi> nor monopolized that vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, which of right belongs vnto Gods miniſters. So that in this caſe they may ſay with good <hi>Samuel, Whoſe oxe haue I taken,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 12.3</note> 
               <hi>or
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:25300:30"/> whoſe aſſe haue I taken, or of whoſe hand haue I receaued any bribe?</hi> They hate ſuch <hi>ſins of vnfaithfulnes,</hi> &amp; they wil not ſuffer the leaſt chip of Gods bread to ſticke on their fingers. By the meanes of ſuch faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> (thankes bee to God, <hi>and remember them herein O God, and wipe not out that kindneſſe that they haue ſhewed on thy houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nehem. 13 14.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; on the offices thereof</hi>) the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious goſpel of Chriſt doth giue a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſtre in many places of this land. But the great number of the other (which I purpoſe not to leaue as yet, for I would gladly make a rod of ſuch ſmall cords as I haue, to whip theſe buyers and ſellers out of the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple) is ſuch, that it doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt overſhadow theſe, that they ſeeme but as it were a handful, and doe beare (I take it) the like proportion, that <hi>Gedions</hi> army did to the huge hoaſt of the <hi>Midi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anites.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iud. 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="16">
               <note place="margin">Hoſpin. de o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rig. templor.</note>16 The donation of Eccleſiaſticall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, was at the firſt, for avoiding of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and confuſion, amongſt the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and ſeditious multitude, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſhould haue made choice of their Paſtours, commended to ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, which for their worth, and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:25300:30"/> &amp; vprightnes were thought fitteſt, both to make choice of ſuch, as could ſufficiently diſcharge the places, and to protect them, &amp; their right againſt ſuch ravenous <hi>harpyes,</hi> and <hi>Eagle-clawed Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzars,</hi> as would ſcrape and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into their hands the veſſels of the temple: and herevpon they were called Patrons. But time is like a river,
<q>
                  <l>—Nec enim conſiſtere flumen,</l>
                  <l>Nec levis hora poteſt.</l>
               </q> That is not my meaning, but as a river ſinkes that which is heavy and ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, &amp; carryeth down that which is light &amp; naught, ſo hath time in this point. The vprightneſſe &amp; faithfulneſſe, that is ſunke long agoe in a great number: their care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe in protecting the miniſters right, that ſwims not downe ſo low as to our time: and yet as <hi>Tully</hi> ſaid of a <hi>tyrant, that he giues life to thoſe that he doth not kill;</hi> ſo we could willingly accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t them worthie maintainers of the <hi>Levites</hi> portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if they would take nothing from them. But the name of <hi>patron,</hi> this is light, and the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of time hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>veied it vnto vs. But (alas alas) it is but as he ſaid,
<q>—ſine corpore nomen.</q>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:25300:31"/> It is <hi>ſecunda not to,</hi> a ſhadow of a name; &amp; yet a name is no more then a ſhaddow of a thing. And verily it may be feared that the great abuſe of the thing wil in future ages make the word to be of a contrary ſignification: as the name<note n="m" place="margin">Iſidor. orig lib. <hi>9.</hi> cap <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>tyrannus,</hi> which at the firſt ſignified any prince, which had a care of his ſubiects ſafety, &amp; protected them againſt their foes; by the cruelty of the governours (handling the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as<note n="n" place="margin">1. Sam. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Samuel</hi> tolde the <hi>Iewes</hi> their king ſhould vſe them; or as the Storke in the fable dealt with the frogs, when he was made their king; or as<note n="o" place="margin">Sueton. in Veſpaſ.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>espaſian</hi> vſed his nobles ſqueazing them like a ſpunge, when they were full) is now degenerate from its ancient ſenſe, &amp; vſed for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. We haue occaſion of doubting the ſame in this point. For <hi>Iudas</hi> claimeth Chriſts bag by preſcription. Is not now the Advouzan of a benefice accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted as a mans proper inheritance? Is it not offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to him that will bid the moſt, as an Oxe in the ſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bles, or an Aſſe in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket? Is it not accounted a good patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to many younger brothers, which ſcorne for ſooth to be Prieſts; and would God they would ſcorne the Prieſts por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:25300:31"/> too, then would they abate a little from the height of their owne conceipts: &amp; would at length be enforced, for their delicate fare, to eate huskes; and to turne their ſatten ſuits into cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try ruſſets. But they are of the ſame opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that was <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rufus</hi> ſometimes king of this Realme,<note n="p" place="margin">Mat. Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſienſis in vita Guil. <hi>2</hi> Rex in proprio te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebat, (die qua obiit) Archiepiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patum Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>8.</hi> Epiſcopatus Wint. &amp; Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risb. cum <hi>11.</hi> Abbatiis.</note> who kept divers biſhopricks in his own hands as they fell, and would not reſtore them vnto eccleſiaſticall perſons. Being demanded a reaſon hereof, he ſaide that Gods bread was ſweete, and good for kings. Or like our old countryman<note n="q" place="margin">Iuſtin.</note> 
               <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> who (when he went about to rob the temple at <hi>Delphos</hi>) ſaide that God was rich, and therfore ſhould part with ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſupply his wants: and, with<note n="r" place="margin">Aelianus variae hiſt. l b <hi>1</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onyſius,</hi> they count golde too colde to cloath <hi>Apollo</hi> with, a garment of worſe ſtuffe is good enough.<note n="ſ" place="margin">In Synodo, Triburienſi An. Do. <hi>895.</hi>
               </note> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was propoſed whether <hi>golden chalices</hi> or <hi>woodden</hi> were to bee vſed in the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſacrament. <hi>Boniface</hi> biſhop and afterwards Martyr,<note n="t" place="margin">Beat. Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanus lib. <hi>2.</hi> rerum Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manicarum.</note> made<note n="ſ" place="margin">In Synodo, Triburienſi An. Do. <hi>895.</hi>
               </note> anſwere that in former times they had <hi>golden mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,</hi> &amp; <hi>woodde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chalices:</hi> but in his time <hi>woodden Prieſts</hi> vſed <hi>golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chalices.</hi> I may ſay the contrary, in the times of our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:25300:32"/> were blockiſh, and woodden Prieſts, and then they had golden cups. Then the people would eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue pulled out their own eies to haue given to thoſe blind guides; and were ſo ready to offer their free gifts to the building of the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, that<note n="u" place="margin">Exod. 36.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> was conſtrained to ſay, <hi>the people bring too much, and more then is enough:</hi> nay moreover, to make a proclamation, &amp; enact a ſtatute, (which yet is in force, but needleſſe) <hi>that neither man, nor woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould prepare any more for the oblation of the ſanctuary.</hi> But now (thanks be to God) wee haue golden pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, and woodden diſhes are thought good enough for them.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Perſius.</note>
               <hi>Dicite pontifices in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plo quid facit auru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</hi> What ſhould the church doe with gold? <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid vnto the <hi>lame</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 3 6.</note> 
               <hi>gold &amp; ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver haue I none.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pſ, 45.14.</note> 
               <hi>The kings daughter is al glorious within,</hi> (they forget what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, <hi>her clothing is of wrought gold</hi>) the miniſters kingdome is not of this world, a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>petent living is ſufficient, that is 40. or 50<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſh, he muſt not be troubled with the thorny cares of this world,<note n="d" place="margin">Num. 16.</note> 
               <hi>yee take too much vpon you yee ſonnes of Levi:</hi> thus would theſe wilde aſſes &amp; <hi>fat buls of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:25300:32"/> beat out of the manger <hi>the oxen that tread out the corne,</hi> that they may haue the beſt themſelues, &amp; leaue only the orts for them, which ſhould haue all. Alas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, that Gods legats, which ſhould be harbarous, &amp; beneficial vnto the poore, and provide for their family, ſhould thus be ſtinted by ſuch, whoſe harts are never ſatisfied with earth, till their mouthes be filled with gravel. But let them not think that the miniſters living is ever co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>petent, where any part of his right is detained. And therfore let them beware how they play the <hi>Iudas</hi> in ſtealing out of the bag, which is committed vnto them, part of that reliefe, which ſhould ſuſtaine Chriſt, &amp; his Apoſtles: or betray him in his main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenance, &amp; by a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, the flocke, by withdrawing their food. For if <hi>Succus pecori,</hi> then it muſt needs follow that <hi>lac ſubducitur agnis:</hi> if the paſture be without the fleece, the flocke ſhal want their fodder. It is an obiection which ſome would faſten as a ſcandal vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Vniverſities, that many of our preachers drone-like lurke in their owne hiues, and flee not abroad; that they bury their talent at home in their own ſtudies
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:25300:33"/> as in the ground; whereas, by ſetling the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in ſome cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try charge, they might put it out to their maſters beſt adva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage. But (ſhall I tell you?) the caſe is with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it was with the ſicke impotent man by the poole <hi>Betheſda</hi> in the 5. of <hi>Iohn,</hi> glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly would they be in the poole, but there is none to put them in: an <hi>angell</hi> troubles the water, and preſently, while they are comming, an other ſteps downe before them. The fountaines are ſtopped; no ſtreame can flow abroad vnleſſe <hi>Tagus-like</hi> it haue golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſands; or, like vnto <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rotas</hi> and <hi>Alpheus,</hi> it paſſe vnder the earth as it were by ſome ſleight and ſecret con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance, and ſo burſt vp on the ſuddaine in ſome place where it cannot be preve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: or like vnto <hi>Tigris,</hi> that fierce and ſwift running river, which perforce wil burſt down ſuch dammes, and bankes as would hinder his courſe: or laſt of all like vnto <hi>Maander</hi> that inſinuating, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſiticall river (as I may call it) which windes, &amp; turnes it ſelfe into every plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant vally, that it may, as it were, get the good wil, and favour of the places where it comes. Theſe 4. rivers finde the eaſieſt paſſage, rich <hi>Tagus,</hi> fierce <hi>Tigris,</hi> ſubtill
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:25300:33"/> 
               <hi>Eurotas,</hi> &amp; winding <hi>Maeandar.</hi> The reſt, for the moſt part, (for I ſpeake not of all) though their waters be as pleaſant as the<note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 2.10</note> 4. rivers of <hi>Eden,</hi> yet ſhall they<note n="f" place="margin">Ioſ. 3.</note> ſtand on a heap, like the waues of <hi>Iordane</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> paſſed over; or as a poole, or the dead ſea without any vent: wheras if there might, at the vacancy of livings, an offer be made vnto one of the Vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, &amp; a choice made thence, no doubte but the goſpell of Chriſt would flouriſh in every quarter of this realme from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> from the river of <hi>Twede</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>lands end.</hi> And God would for this cauſe even <hi>open the windowes of heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the inhabitants thereof, and powre down vpon them a bleſſing without meaſure, and rebuke the devourer for their ſakes, that he ſhould not deſtroy the fruits of their grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, neither ſhoulde their vine bee barren in the field,</hi> as the Lord ſpeakes by the Prophet<note n="g" place="margin">Mal. 3.10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>Malachie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17 I haue dwelt too long vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this point. Only to end, I would theſe men woulde remember <hi>Iudas</hi> his end. <hi>Demiror te An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonî quorum facta imitaris eorum exitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> phorreſcere.</hi> It is the ſaying of<note n="h" place="margin">Philippice 2.</note> 
               <hi>Tully</hi> to <hi>Antony.</hi> I wonder <hi>Antony</hi> that thou art
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:25300:34"/> not afraid of thoſe mens deaths, whoſe liues thou imitateſt. And it is ſtrange that theſe men will bee like vnto <hi>Iudas</hi> in the premiſes, and never thinke of the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that was inferred therevpon.<note n="i" place="margin">Amos 7.14.</note> 
               <hi>I am not a Prophet, nor am I the ſonne of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,</hi> that I ſhould foretell the manner of their particular ruines. Thus much vpon good grounds I wil ſay, that theſe goods wil in time profit them no more, then the price of him, that was valued, availed <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das:</hi> they will bee like<note n="k" place="margin">Plin. lib. <hi>10</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> Eagles feathers; they will eate, &amp; conſume the reſt of their ſubſtance: or like <hi>equui Scianus</hi> &amp; <hi>aurum Toloſſanum</hi> in<note n="l" place="margin">A Gell. lib. <hi>10</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gellius,</hi> which were ſtill infortunate to thoſe that had them. And thoſe goodly buildings, which they make for themſelues with the ruines of Gods houſe (I will ſpeake in the words of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> againſt the enemies of the church)<note n="m" place="margin">Iſa. 34.11 13. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>the Pellican and the hedgehogge ſhall poſſeſſe them, the great raven, and the owle ſhall dwell in them, and he ſhall ſtretch out vpon them the line of vanitie, and the ſtones of emptineſſe: they ſhall bring forth thornes in the palaces thereof, nettles and thiſtles in the ſtrong holds thereof, &amp; they ſhall be habitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for dragons, &amp; courts for
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:25300:34"/> Oſtriches: there ſhall meet</hi> Zim, <hi>&amp;</hi> Iim, <hi>&amp; the faeries ſhall dance there, &amp; the ſkrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owle ſhall reſt there, and ſhall finde for her ſelfe a quiet dwelling: there ſhall the owle make her neſt, and lay, and hatch, &amp; gather them vnder her ſhadow; there ſhall the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures alſo be gathered, every one with her mate. Seeke in the booke of God and read: none of theſe ſhall fayle.</hi> For more confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation hereof, conſider the ſubverſion of <hi>Abbies:</hi> they were founded by religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men in their generations, to a good purpoſe: their ſituation was as the<note n="n" place="margin">Gen. 13.10.</note> 
               <hi>gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the Lord, like the land of Egypt as thou goeſt vnto Zoar;</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeakes of the plaine of <hi>Iordan before the deſtruction of Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorah:</hi> they ſtretched their towers vp to the heavens, like the <hi>Pyramides</hi> of <hi>Egypt;</hi> but, behold, the Lord <hi>hath wiped them as a man wipeth a diſh, which hee wipeth, and turneth vpſide down.</hi> They are now the fitteſt places for the raven to build in, habitations for dra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gons, and courts for Oſtriches, they ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, (but as<note n="o" place="margin">Phyſ. c.</note> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, <hi>quod ſtat move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> they ſtand ſo as they are mouing to a fall) in the pleaſanteſt vallies of the land, as the reliques of <hi>Babel</hi> in the vallie of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:25300:35"/> 
               <hi>Sinar:</hi> or<note n="p" place="margin">Iſa. 7.8.</note> 
               <hi>like a cottage in a vineyard, like a lodge in a garden of cucumbers, and like a beſieged &amp; defaced city,</hi> dropping down by ioints, as a theefe rotteth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet. What were their ſins which brought ſo heavie a iudgement vpon them? ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they were (as they were indeed) the ſinnes of <hi>Sodome,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Ezech. 16 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note> 
               <hi>pride, fulneſſe of bread, mercileſneſſe towards the poore, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of idleneſſe.</hi> Now if theſe ſinnes of ſome fewe, or ſuppoſe the greater part (certaine it is that al were not ſuch, ſome were induſtrious, ſome humble, ſome mercifull towardes the needy, ſome of a moderate and ſpare dyet,) if theſe ſinnes, I ſay, brought ſo heavy a iudgement vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe houſes, that they are, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of that they were before, like the ſtumpe of<note n="r" place="margin">1. Sam. 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>Dagon,</hi> when his head, &amp; the two palmes of his hands were cut of vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the threſhold in <hi>Aſhdod;</hi> or the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainders of <hi>Iezabel,</hi> when the hungry dogges had eaten her vp, ſo that<note n="ſ" place="margin">2. King 9.35.37.</note> 
               <hi>there was no more found of her, then the skull, and the feet, and the palmes of her hands;</hi> inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, <hi>that none can ſay this is Iezabel;</hi> theſe bee the houſes they were before: ſhall wee thinke that their houſes ſhall
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:25300:35"/> continue for ever, which turne <hi>Bethel</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Bethaven;</hi> the houſe of God, into a houſe of vanitie; which take the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s bread and caſt it vnto dogges? which, with the conſecrated things of the altar, maintaine their owne pompe, feed their Haukes, their Horſes, keepe—? but I ſtay my ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="18">18 After the <hi>Church-robber</hi> comes the <hi>grinding oppreſſour,</hi> another great <hi>plague,</hi> which ſits ſore vpon the skirts of our land. He ſaith vnto his gold, thou art my God,<note n="t" place="margin">Iob 31.24</note> 
               <hi>and to the wedge of gold, thou art my confidence.</hi> And inſteed of counting<note n="u" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>godlineſſe great gaine,</hi> hee accounteth <hi>gaine great godlineſſe:</hi> he addeth houſe to houſe, and land to land, as if the way to the ſpirituall <hi>Canaan</hi> laid all by land, and not through a red ſea of death. He bray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the people as in a mortar, &amp; grindeth the faces of the poore.<note n="a" place="margin">Amos 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hee ſelleth the poore for ſilver, and the needy for a paire of ſhooes:</hi> hee eateth vp the poore as if they were bread.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Vt piſces ſaepe minutos</l>
               <l>Magnu' comeſt, vt aves enecat aceipter,</l>
            </q>
            <p>As a Pike devoureth the little fiſhes, and as a goſhauke kills the ſmaller birds: hee
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:25300:36"/> gathereth the livings of the poorer ſort into his owne hands, as the great <hi>Ocean</hi> drinketh the rivers: hee enhaunceth his rents, and pilleth his poore tenants, and doubleth, yea, treableth their fines, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them, with young<note n="b" place="margin">Kin. 12.10</note> 
               <hi>Rhehoboam,</hi> that <hi>his little finger ſhall be heavier then his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers loines.</hi> Not contented with this cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eltie, he thruſteth them out of their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and depopulateth whole townes, &amp; villages, making thoſe ſtreets which vſed to be ſowne with the ſeed of men,<note n="c" place="margin">Iſa. 7.25.</note> 
               <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures for the ſending out of bullocks, and for the treading of ſheepe.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Apud Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. in deſcript. Northampt.</note> One iuſtly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſheep: that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in former times, they were the mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt beaſts of the field, &amp; contented the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with a little, are now become ſo fierce, &amp; greedie, that they devoure men, and towne fields, and houſes, &amp; villages, &amp; lay all waſt; inſomuch that that which the Pſalmiſt ſpeaketh of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſpoiled by his enimies, may be verified of our <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> alſo: <hi>They haue devoured Iacob, and laid waſt his dwelling places.</hi> Surely, the<note n="e" place="margin">Hab. 2.11 12.</note> 
               <hi>very ſtone out of the wall doth cry againſt theſe men, and the beame out of the timber doth anſwer it: woe vnto him that buildeth
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:25300:36"/> his houſe with blood, and erecteth his walls by iniquitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While the ſpleene ſwelleth, the body languiſheth: and it may iuſtly bee feared, that if our <hi>good Phyſitian</hi> doe not in time purge theſe tumorous, and ſwelling me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, they will cauſe a <hi>lienterie</hi> in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy politicke. God forbid that this flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing kingdome, which ſometime hath deſerued that title which<note n="f" place="margin">Iuſtin</note> 
               <hi>Cyneus,</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour vnto <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> gaue vnto <hi>Rome</hi> when he called it a <hi>Citie of Kings,</hi> ſhould ever deſerue that title, which<note n="g" place="margin">Aventinus</note> one giues vnto <hi>France,</hi> when he calls it a <hi>kingdome of aſſes,</hi> by reaſon of the burdens, that are laid vpon the baſer ſort by their ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours.</p>
            <p n="19">19 Therefore it behoues you, &amp; as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my as ſit at the ſterne of iuſtice, not to ſleepe with <hi>Ionas,</hi> while the ſhip is toſſed with theſe mightie winds: nor to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in a matter ſo neerely concerning the good of this Common-wealth.<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>Gird you with your ſwordes vpon your thighes, O yee men of might, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your worſhippe, and renowne, ride on becauſe of the word of truth, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, &amp; let your right hand teach you ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:25300:37"/> things.</hi> But if you ſhal be negligent herein, ſurely, as <hi>Mordecai</hi> ſaid to <hi>Heſter,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Eſt. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>helpe, and deliverance ſhall come from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other place.</hi> For doubtleſſe the crie of the afflicted, is already aſcended, into the cares of the Lord of hoſts, &amp; he will take the matter into his owne hand. Beleeue it, it is his owne promiſe:<note n="k" place="margin">Pſ. 12.5, 6</note> 
               <hi>Now for the comfortleſſe troubles ſake of the needie, &amp; becauſe of the deepe ſighing of the poore, I will vp, ſaith God, and will deliver him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch as vex him, &amp; will restore him to reſt.</hi> I will proſecute this point no further: only let mee tell theſe <hi>locuſts,</hi> that their goods whervnto they truſt<note n="l" place="margin">2. King. 28 21.</note> 
               <hi>are but a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſtaffe of reed, wherevnto if a man leane it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll peirce into his hand:</hi> that their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures are but as<note n="m" place="margin">Iud. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Dalilah</hi> was to <hi>Samſon</hi> even giues and fetters of Satan, to entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle them: that their gold will be as a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone about their neckes, to carrie them downe headlong into the pit: that their lands &amp; goods are as a <hi>bunch</hi> vpon a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels backe,</hi> which will not ſuffer them to enter in at the <hi>needles eie,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 19.24.</note> the <hi>narrow way that leadeth to heaven:</hi> that thoſe goods, which by grinding, and oppreſſing they haue ſcraped together, the Lord will <hi>fan
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:25300:37"/> them away with the fan of vanitie,</hi> vnleſſe (as<note n="o" place="margin">Dan. 4.24</note> 
               <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaid to <hi>Nabuchadnezzar) they breake off their ſinnes by righteouſnes, and their iniquitie by mercy towardes the poore;</hi> &amp; that which they haue by vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes gotten (with <hi>Zachaeus</hi>)<note n="p" place="margin">Luk. 19.8</note> 
               <hi>they reſtore it againe foure-fold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20 From the <hi>Locuſt,</hi> wee come to the <hi>Cankar-worme;</hi> from <hi>oppreſſing Ahab,</hi> to <hi>bribing Gehazi:</hi> of whom I may truely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that which<note n="q" place="margin">Hiſt. lib. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſpeakes of the <hi>Aſtrologians</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> it is <hi>genus hominum peſtilens, &amp; fallax, quod in hac republicae ſemper prohibetur, &amp; ſemper retinetur;</hi> a peſtilent, and froward kind of people, which hath beene ſtill gaine ſaid, and yet never more common, and frequent then now; an ofſpring, not ſo degenerate from the Ioines of <hi>Iudas,</hi> as is the <hi>oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour.</hi> Becauſe the <hi>oppreſſour</hi> like the <hi>fat Buls of Baſan, cloſeth the poore on every ſide, and gapes vpon him with his mouth, as it were a ramping, &amp; a roaring lion;</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the <hi>briber</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Pſa. 10.8.10.</note> 
               <hi>lieth cloſely in the theeuiſh corners of the ſtreets, that hee may raviſh ſuch as he ſhall get into his net.</hi> The <hi>oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour</hi> takes it perforce, the <hi>briber</hi> gets all by ſecret compact<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>What will yee giue me?</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:25300:38"/>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Eſt 4.11.</note> None might come <hi>to the inner court of king Ahaſhueroſh, ſaue hee, to whom the king held out his golden ſcepter.</hi> But none may come to the <hi>bribers</hi> inner court, ſaue hee, that ſhall hold out a golden ſcepter vnto him. Be thy cauſe never ſo light in the balance of equitie, it is not material, if thou canſt make it vp in gold, it ſhall be currant through his liberties. Right and wrong, truth, and falſhood are onely diſtinguiſhed by their attendants. If in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice get the overthrowe, it is becauſe ſhee is not garded with ſuch companies, as are expected. But I haue not <hi>Eliſhaes</hi> eies, to point out <hi>Gehazi,</hi> and to obſerue what he hath done in ſecret, &amp; therefore I will paſſe him over: onely thus much I would haue him to knowe, that <hi>Iudas</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo ſecretly compact with the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> but Chriſt knoweth it. That ſpeech of our bleſſed Saviour (which that worthy Martyr <hi>Hugh Latimer</hi> vſed for his poſie) is an vndoubted truth: <hi>There is nothing ſo ſecret, but it ſhall bee revealed.</hi> Thou maiſt well flatter thy ſelfe with an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhew of iuſtice, like that monſter in the<note n="t" place="margin">Hor. epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> lib. <hi>1.</hi> ep. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.</hi>
               </note> Poet:
<q>
                  <l>—Pulchra Laverna</l>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:25300:38"/>
                  <l>Da mihi fallere, da ſanctum iuſtum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> videri:</l>
                  <l>Noctem peccatis, &amp; fraudibus obijce nubem.</l>
               </q> O beautifull <hi>Laverna,</hi> grant that I may deceaue the world with a counterfeit ſhew of holineſſe: cover my ſinnes with a cloud of obſcuritie, that they may bee hid. Deceaue the world thou maiſt, but thou canſt not deceaue God.</p>
            <q>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Ov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. met.</note>Sol oculis hominem, quibus aspicit omnia cernit:</q>
            <p>God, whoſe eies are ten thouſand times brighter then the ſun, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pierce through this cloud, if it were darker then hell, and behold thy doing. It is no heatheniſh cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell, which a heathen man giues, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth it ſmell of Epicuriſme, though it was his dictate, who was the father of that ſwiniſh ſect,<note n="a" place="margin">Epicurus apud Sence.</note> that <hi>whatſoever thou art about to doe, though never ſo ſecret, thou ſhouldst ſtill imagine, that ſome doth behold thee, and obſerue thy actions. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſic tanquam illo spectante vivas, &amp; omnia ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam illo vidente facias,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca.</hi> And therefore whatſoever thou art about to doe, ſaith the ſame writer, imagine that <hi>Cato,</hi> a ſevere reprehender of the leaſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:25300:39"/> or (if this be too much) ſuppoſe that <hi>Laelius,</hi> a man of a quiet diſpoſition, but ſuch as cannot brooke any notable of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, doth behold thee. This is good counſell of a heathen man, which knewe not God aright. But thou, which doeſt profeſſe Chriſtianitie, ſhouldſt goe a ſtep further, and fully aſſure thy ſelfe, that not a ſinfull man, but that a ſinne-revenging God doth watch thee. <hi>Propè à te Deus eſt, tecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, intùs eſt.</hi> And, <hi>Sacer in te spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus ſedet, bonorum malorum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, &amp; cuſtos,</hi> as the heathen <hi>Stoicke</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely ſpeaketh: there is a holy ſpirit within thee, which ſeeth whatſoever thou doeſt, good or bad. Do not then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue thy ſelfe like that Sophiſter in<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſt. anal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle,</hi> who thought it impoſſible to know by demonſtration, the affections of a number or triangle, becauſe he kept ſome number or tria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gle in his fiſt, which othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s did not knowe of. Be it <hi>Nummus,</hi> or <hi>Numerus,</hi> triangle, or croſſe, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it bee, thou canſt not keepe it ſo cloſely in thy hand, but God lookes into it, and will one day call thee to an accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for it.</p>
            <p n="21">21 In the laſt place, comes the <hi>Graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hopper,</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:25300:39"/> the <hi>cozening Lawyer,</hi> who feedes his client with ſugered words, &amp; golden hopes, but al proues in the end for a <hi>quid mihi dabitis?</hi> Here, as <hi>Tullie</hi> ſaid vnto the <hi>Romans</hi> touching the <hi>Catilinarians; Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio me Patres Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcripti eſſe clementem, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio non diſſolutum videri;</hi> I would gladly hold my peace, and not bee iudged by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to exceed the limits of modeſtie. But <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oces reip. imò totius regni me nequitiae inertiae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> condemnarent:</hi> the voice of the whole kingdome, exclaiming againſt the great abuſes of theſe times, would condemne me of negligence. The time is protracted, vnneceſſarie delaies are vſed, newe doubts are dayly inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, inſomuch that the cauſes are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes more vncertaine in the latter end, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were at the firſt beginning. What poſtings off from court to court! what delaies and procraſtinations from tearme, to tearme, from yeare to yeare! in ſomuch, that a man may ſooner travel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the whole globe of the earth, then paſſe through an <hi>Engliſh</hi> court. The laws are made like a game at the cards, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all the players are looſers, and all the gaine comes to the butler, which founde
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:25300:40"/> them cards to play on. And the lawyers proue ſuch arbitratours, as was <hi>Quintus Fabius</hi> in <hi>Tullie;</hi> who, being appointed a daieſman betweene the <hi>Nolanes,</hi> and the <hi>Neopolitanes,</hi> touching the borders of their grounds, tooke a great part of their right from both: or rather like to <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon;</hi> who, being choſen a iudge betweene two brethren, touching their fathers kingdome, took it from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both, and reſerved it to himſelfe. They take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both the parties, though not the ſame <hi>numero,</hi> which they contend for, yet the ſame <hi>ſpecie,</hi> (I meane the value of the ſame) and gaine it to themſelues. The ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſheepe in a tempeſt runnes to a briar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh for a ſhelter: when the ſtorme is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verblowne, he is ſo claſped in the briars, that before hee get out, he is enforced to leaue ſome good parte of his fleece be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde him, ſo that he is made vnable to endure the next ſtorme. And yet better it is that he ſhould indure it with patience, then, by having recourſe to ſuch an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, haue his skin ripped by the bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. I will not apply. I reverence the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. It is good, and neceſſary for the commonwealth and a calling warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:25300:40"/> by Gods word. And I make no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion but there are many of this profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which doe ſtudy to approue their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the ſight of God and man. And ſo I am perſwaded of you all, though I thus ſpeake: but as the<note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 4.4</note> 
               <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: <hi>I know nothing of my ſelfe, yet am I not iuſtified,</hi> ſo ſay I, though I know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by any of you, yet I am not iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. I do not diſcharge a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, vnleſſe I ſhould admoniſh you of theſe things; that if any be guilty of that which I haue ſpoken, he may learne to amend it: if not, he may do his endeavour to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voide it.</p>
            <p n="22">22 If I ſhould ſpeake vnto you, <hi>(R. H.)</hi> and offer to inſtruct you in the particular duties of a iudge, I might perchance be iudged by many, with<note n="d" place="margin">Aelian. Var. hiſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Megabizus</hi> to diſcourſe of the art of painting, before the ſchollers of <hi>Zeuxis.</hi> To ſay nothing, that my text giues me no fit occaſion to diſcourſe of this ſubiect, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding I beſeech you, in one word giue me leaue to moue you to that, which yee both know, &amp; are ready, I am ſure, to put in pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctiſe. You know the ſaying of the <hi>Poet,</hi>
               <q>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:25300:41"/>
                  <l>Qui rogat vt facias, quod iam facis, ipſe rogando</l>
                  <l>Laudat, et hortatu comprobat acta ſuo.</l>
               </q> The obiect of your office is either <hi>life,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or <hi>liuing.</hi> About both theſe, it is requiſite you haue 3 properties; an <hi>eagles eie,</hi> a <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies hand,</hi> and a <hi>lyons heart.</hi> An <hi>eagles eie,</hi> to diue into the bottome of ſuch matters as ſhall come before you: for the wound is never ſoundly cured, vnleſſe the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome be firſt ſearched. A <hi>ladies hand,</hi> to deale ſoftly, and gently with your pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents. A <hi>lyons heart,</hi> to be couragious, and reſolute, when there is no place for lenity. Herein yee muſt imitate a good Surgeon, who cuts the wound, though his patient weepe never ſo ſore.<note n="e" place="margin">Aug. in Mat. Ser. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Plorat ſecandus &amp; ſecatur plorat vrendus &amp; vri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> The ſicke weepes, and yet the Surge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cuts, the ſicke laments, &amp; yet the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon ſeareth. Is this cruelty in the Surge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? none at all. For, <hi>ſaevit in vulnus, vt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ſanetur: quia ſi vulnus palpetur, homo perditur.</hi> Where there is hope of cure without ſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, or cutting, vſe there a ladies hand; in this caſe a plaſter is better then a knife. But where the member is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable, and incorrigible, and like to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:25300:41"/> the whole, cut it off, <hi>Melius eſt vt pereat vnus, quàm vnitas.</hi> And,
<q>—immedicabile vulnus</q> 
               <hi>Enſe recide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dum, ne pars ſyncera trahatur.</hi> But yet <hi>Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cta prius tentanda;</hi> fire muſt be the laſt medicine. All gentle meanes muſt be firſt tried: and even in this act of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, yee muſt not altogither exclude mercy.<note n="f" place="margin">Plutare. de audiendis poetis,</note> When many of the <hi>Lacedaemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> were drunke with wine, <hi>Lycurgus</hi> gaue charge that the vines ſhould be cut downe; but <hi>Platoes</hi> counſell was better, who willed, that the fountaines ſhoulde be cauſed to run amongſt the Vines, and that the rage of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> ſhould be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered with the ſobernes of <hi>Neptune,</hi> that is, that the water ſhould be mingled with the wine. Though the extremity of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice make ſome deſperate, (as did <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co's</hi> laws, which for their ſeverity are ſaid to be written in blood) yet muſt it not therefore be taken away, but rather the rigour of iuſtice muſt be mixed with cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, as his counſell was, that the rage of wine ſhoulde bee aſſwaged with the cooleneſſe of the water. For iuſtice with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mercy is bloudy cruelty, mercy with out iuſtice is fooliſh pity; but iuſtice with
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:25300:42"/> mercy is perfect Chriſtianity. Oh then, thoſe which God would haue ioined to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, doe not you put aſunder. But let them both be ſo linked togither, that yee may verifie that of the<note n="g" place="margin">Pſ. 85.10.</note> 
               <hi>Pſalmiſt, Mercy and truth are met togither, righteouſnes, and peace haue kiſſed each other.</hi> To this purpoſe, in all your conſultations, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions <hi>ſet God before your eies.</hi> Let him be on your right handes, and <hi>ſo yee ſhall not greatly fall.</hi> A <hi>Poet,</hi> when he is to bring a perſon vpon the ſtage, wil haue this care, that the action, and ſpeech be agreeable to the perſon.</p>
            <q>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Hor. de art Poet.</note>Intercrit multum, Davuſne lo quatur, an Heros:</q>
            <p>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Cicero.</note>
               <hi>Id hiſtrio videbit in Scena, quod non ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens in vita?</hi> ſhall a ſtage-player obſerue that <hi>decoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> on the theater, which a wiſe man will not looke to in his life? The world is a ſtage, &amp; every man acteth his part vpon this ſtage. You <hi>(R. H.)</hi> doe act the part of God himſelfe. The more wary ought ye to be in your actions. Ever wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, whether God, if he were in your places, would do thus, or thus. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber likewiſe, that, though ye be Gods, yet ye muſt die as a man. The greateſt
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:25300:42"/> iudge of the earth muſt one day hold vp his hand at the barre, and anſwer for him ſelfe, when the iudge of the world ſhall ſit on the bench. This do, &amp; when it ſhall pleaſe God to call you hence, yee ſhalbe advanced to a higher court, the court of heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where, for your ſcarlet garments, yee ſhall be inveſted<note n="k" place="margin">Rev. 7.15</note> 
               <hi>in long white robes,</hi> your bench ſhall be the throne, your at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants the Angels, the parties yee ſhall iudge,<note n="l" place="margin">1 Cor 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>the world,</hi> your ſentence an <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leluiah: Amen, praiſe, and glory, and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and thankes, and honour, and power, and might bee vnto our God for evermore Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:25300:43"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25300:43"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 82.6.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I haue ſaid, yee are Gods; but yee ſhall die like men.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are 3. ſortes of men, who, if they bee faithfull in their places, and followe the directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their bookes, are the chiefe pillars, to ſupport a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an commonwealth: the <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,</hi> and the <hi>Magiſtrate.</hi> Theſe 3. are in the body <hi>politicke;</hi> as the three principall parts, the <hi>liver,</hi> the <hi>heart,</hi> and the <hi>braine</hi> are in the body of <hi>man.</hi> The <hi>Phyſitian</hi> is the <hi>liver,</hi> the <hi>Divine</hi> is the <hi>heart,</hi> and the <hi>Magistrate</hi> is the <hi>braine</hi> of the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. The <hi>liver</hi> is called <hi>the beginning of the naturall faculty;</hi> it ſegregareth the humours, it ingendreth alimental blood, &amp; by vaines ſends it into each part of the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:25300:44"/> body, whereby the whole is nouriſhed, and preſerued. Like vnto it is the <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian,</hi> who purgeth the body of man, from ſuch noxious humours, as whereby it may be endangered, &amp; preſcribeth ſuch a diet, as whereby it may be beſt nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and kept in health. <hi>The heart</hi> is called <hi>the beginning of the vitall facultie,</hi> it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendreth the vitall ſpirits, and by arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſendeth them into every particular member. To which I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare the <hi>Divine.</hi> For as the <hi>heart</hi> is the fountaine of the vitall ſpirits, &amp; the beginning of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall facultie: ſo is the <hi>Divine</hi> the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine and beginning, though not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of generation, nor <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of radication, yet <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (to vſe the <hi>Phyſitians</hi> tearmes) of the diſpenſation of the true vitall ſpirit. <hi>Hee</hi> is the meanes to make thee, of a naturall man (ſuch as the <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian</hi> leaueth thee) a ſpirituall ſubſtance. The <hi>braine,</hi> which is called <hi>the beginning of the animal facultie,</hi> is the chiefe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der of the whole: it ſitteth in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt roome, as in a ſtately palace, being compaſſed about with the <hi>pericranium,</hi> the <hi>cranium,</hi> and the two <hi>meninges,</hi> as ſo many ſtrong caſtles, and countermures,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:25300:44"/> againſt all forraine invaſion. It hath the fiue externall ſenſes as intelligencers, to giue notice, what is done abroad, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe, the phantaſie, and the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding as privie counſellers, the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie as a booke of recordes. But yet it is not idle, but is continually buſied in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering the ſpirits receiued from the hart: which it ſendeth by the nerues, through the whole body, thereby giuing ſenſe, &amp; motion to every part. A fit embleme of a good <hi>Magistrate,</hi> who as hee hath his forts, and gard, and counſellours, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, &amp;c. ſo muſt he remember that hee hath not theſe for his owne proper vſe, but for the whole, and therefore ſhould beſtir himſelfe, for benefitting the whol, eſpecially in tempering the ſpirits recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the heart; I mean in vſing thoſe ſpirituall admonitions, and inſtructions, which he ſhall receaue from the miniſter of the Goſpell, for the good, and benefit of all thoſe that are vnder him. As the body is in beſt eſtate, when all theſe are wel diſpoſed, ſo it is moſt miſerable, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is a <hi>dyſcraſie,</hi> and diſtemperature in any of them. So in the <hi>ſtate</hi> likewiſe: Wo vnto that Common-wealth where the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:25300:45"/> 
               <hi>Phyſitian</hi> for wholſome phyſicke mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreth <hi>hemlocke:</hi> &amp; the <hi>Divine,</hi> for ſound doctrine, broacheth <hi>hereſie,</hi> and the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate</hi> turneth iuſtice into wormwood. Of all theſe three, the <hi>braine</hi> is ſubiect to moſt diſeaſes: and of all theſe three, the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> is moſt obnoxious to falls; both becauſe he hath many incitements vnto ſin, which others want; &amp; becauſe he is depriued of a benefit, which others haue, that is, he is not ſo freely reproued for his offences, as commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly others are; And laſtly becauſe of thoſe <hi>Cubiculares conſiliarij,</hi> (as<note n="a" place="margin">Polit. lib. <hi>3</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lipſius</hi> cals them) <hi>tineae &amp; ſorices Palatij,</hi> (as <hi>Conſtantine</hi> tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them) the very mothes and rats of a court, which liue by other mens harmes; <hi>à quibus bonus, prudent, cautus venditur imperator,</hi> (as<note n="b" place="margin">Vopi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c. in Aureliano.</note> 
               <hi>Diocleſian</hi> an ill Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour ſaid well) which ſell the magiſtrates favours, as if one would ſell ſmoake, (as did<note n="c" place="margin">Lamprid. Ant. Heliog.</note> 
               <hi>Zoticus</hi> the faire promiſes of <hi>Helio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabalus</hi>) and are alwaies ready, for their own advantage, to giue an applauſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his worſt actions. By theſe he is ledde whitherſoever they will haue him,
<q>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Hor.</note>Ducitur vt nervis alienis mobilc lignum.</q>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:25300:45"/> Eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as an arrow is led by the bow-ſtring. Therefore <hi>David</hi> in this Pſalme maketh a ſharpe ſermon againſt the corruption of <hi>Magiſtrats,</hi> out of which I haue made choice of this one branch. <hi>I haue ſaid, yee are Gods; but yee ſhall die like men.</hi> As if he had ſaid: truth it is, your autority is great, your power extraordinary, <hi>(yee are Gods)</hi> yet<note n="e" place="margin">Pſ. 75.6.</note> 
               <hi>ſet not vp your hornes on high, and ſpeake not with a ſtiffe necke,</hi> yee are no tranſcendents, ye haue no more reaſon to boaſt of your ſuperioritie, then the moon hath to bragge of the light, which ſhee borroweth from the ſunne, or the wal of the beame, which it receaues in at the window; yee haue it only from me <hi>(I haue ſaid:)</hi> &amp; though yee be <hi>Gods,</hi> yet yee are but earthly <hi>Gods,</hi> yee are <hi>Gods</hi> in office, not <hi>Gods</hi> in eſſence, yee are made of the ſame mettall that others are, &amp; your end ſhall be like other mens <hi>(you ſhall die like men.)</hi> In which words, not to ſtand vpon the divers acceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of any of them, may it pleaſe you to obſerue theſe 3 points. 1. The partie from whom Magiſtrates re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue their authoritie, it is from God, <hi>(I haue ſaid)</hi> and Gods ſaying is his doing. 2. Their preheminence aboue others, in
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:25300:46"/> that they are called Gods <hi>(yee are Gods)</hi> 3. The limitation of their dignity, <hi>ye ſhall die as men.</hi> Out of which I collect theſe 3. propoſitions. 1 <hi>Magiſtrats and Iudges of the earth doe receaue their autoritie from God.</hi> 2. <hi>They are Gods deputies to miniſter iuſtice, &amp; to iudge between party &amp; partie.</hi> 3. <hi>Though they be extolled aboue their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren according to their office, yet they muſt dy as other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> where is implied this gene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rall concluſion, <hi>that it is the lot of all men, once to die.</hi> Theſe are the pillars of my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended diſcourſe: of which while I ſhall plainely entreat, in the ſame order, that I haue now propoſed them, I beſeech you all to afford me your Chriſtian attention.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Of all the corporeall creatures that God made,<note place="margin">1. Part.</note> none is more exorbitant then man. The higheſt <hi>moueable</hi> is conſtant in his motion. He doth not haſten, nor neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect his courſe. The <hi>ſunne</hi> is preciſe in his courſe vnder the <hi>Eclipticke line,</hi> &amp; turneth not an haire breadth, vnto the right hand or vnto the left, but<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 19.5</note> 
               <hi>commeth forth as a bridegroome out of his chamber, and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth as a giant to run his race.</hi> The reſt of the <hi>Planets,</hi> though they turne to both ſides of the <hi>Zodiake,</hi> and are (the moſt of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:25300:46"/> them) ſometimes <hi>direct,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>ſtationarie,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>retrograde</hi> (as Aſtronomers ſpeake) by reaſon of their motion in their imaginarie <hi>Epicicles,</hi> yet they haue their conſtancie in this incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie. Thou (O God) <hi>haſt giuen them a law that ſhall not be broken.</hi> The elements keepe themſelues within their boundes. The beaſts of the forreſt, in their kinde, haue their policie, and ſocietie. The ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ſea goes not beyond his limits: God hath bound it (to vſe<note n="g" place="margin">Iob. 38.</note> 
               <hi>Iobs</hi> words) <hi>as a child in ſwadling bands: hee hath giuen it doores, and barres, and ſaid vnto it, hither ſhalt thou goe, &amp; thou ſhalt goe no further, here ſhalt thou ſtay thy proud waues.</hi> But man is more exorbitant then all theſe: no bounds can keepe him in. Therefore God hath written in the heart, and conſcience of every man, that comes into the world, a law, which wee call the law of nature: as that <hi>God is to be worſhipped, good is to be embraced, evil is to be avoided. That which thou wouldeſt not another man ſhould doe vnto thee, thou muſt not doe to another ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And according to theſe generall noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, hee would haue every perſon to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect his actions. But this law (like an old
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:25300:47"/> inſcription vpon a ſtone) is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſtonie heart of man in ſuch blind charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that he is put to his ſhifts before hee ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpell it. And howſoever he vnderſtand it in <hi>Theſi,</hi> yet in <hi>Hypotheſi,</hi> in the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, he makes many ſoloeciſmes, and ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times calls good evill, and evill good. Therefore God hath written with his own finger a paraphraſe vpon it, which we call the morall law, and added a large commentarie of iudiciall lawes, by the hand of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Which benefit (though not the ſame <hi>numero</hi>) he hath not onely granted vnto Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Commonwealths, but even to the heathen alſo, amongſt whom, in all ages, he hath ſtirred vp men of excellent ſpirit to make lawes, for the better government of their ſeveral ſtates. The beſt of which did acknowledge that they had them from God. Howbeit after the cuſtome of nations, which held a plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie of Gods, they did not all agree in one name;<note n="h" place="margin">Diodorus Siculus.</note> 
               <hi>Lycurgus</hi> affirming that hee receaued his lawes from <hi>Apollo, Mino<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> from <hi>Iupiter, Solon,</hi> and <hi>Draco</hi> from <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerva, Numa</hi> from the <hi>Nymph Egeria, Anacharſis</hi> from <hi>Zamolxis</hi> the <hi>Scythian</hi> God.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:25300:47"/>3 But all this will not confine man within his boundes, for it is true of him, which was ſpoken of the <hi>Athenians,</hi> that they knewe what was to bee done, &amp; yet did it not. And, which was obiected by the <hi>Cynicke,</hi> againſt the old Philoſophers of <hi>Greece,</hi> that they gaue good rules, but put none in practiſe.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—<note n="i" place="margin">Ovid. Met</note> video meliora probo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </l>
               <l>Deteriora ſequor,—</l>
            </q>
            <p>ſaid <hi>Medea</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe was overcome with paſſion. It is true of moſt men, though they know the law, how that they which commit ſin, are worthy of death,<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 1.31</note> yet they do not only the ſame themſelues, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo favour them that doe it. The law of it ſelfe is but a dead letter. It is like a ſword in the warres without a ſouldier to draw it. Many make no more account of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing it, then<note n="l" place="margin">Liv. lib. <hi>1.</hi> dec. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Remus</hi> did of going o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the furrow, which <hi>Romulus</hi> had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be drawne. Or the <hi>frogs</hi> in the fable of skipping over the <hi>Lion,</hi> when he was faſt a ſleepe. Therefore God hath added the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> as the life, and ſoule of the lawe, as a Captaine to manage this ſworde. Him hee hath made (if I may ſo ſpeake) the <hi>ſummum genus</hi> of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:25300:48"/> by two <hi>genericall differences</hi> of <hi>poena,</hi> and <hi>praemium,</hi> to coarct, and keepe his inferiours in their ſeverall ranks: that as <hi>Iehu,</hi> and <hi>Iehonadab,</hi> went hand in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d togither, for the rooting out of <hi>Ahabs</hi> poſterity, &amp; deſtruction of <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts; ſo the <hi>magiſtrate</hi> being (as<note n="m" place="margin">Ethicoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> cals him) a living law, and the law, being a mute, &amp; dead <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> ſhould ioine hand in hand, and proceed valorouſly, to the rooting out of ſin, the ſuppreſſion of Idolatry, the protection of iuſtice, and maintenance of true religion.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Now that <hi>they haue this autority only from God,</hi> it is a point, which I hope in this place, I ſhall not need long to inſiſt vpon.<note n="n" place="margin">Iam 1.17</note> 
               <hi>For if every good and perfect gift be frome aboue, even from the father of lights,</hi> much more this excellent, and ſuperemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t gift of governing Gods people, muſt proceed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this fountaine. And to think otherwiſe is but with the <hi>Epicures,</hi> to be of opinion, that though God made the world, yet the government thereof, hee leaveth to <hi>fortunes</hi> diſcretion, to be dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by her. One of the ſtiles wherewith God is inveſted, is this, that<note n="o" place="margin">1. Cor. 14</note> 
               <hi>he is the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of order, and not of confuſion: if of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:25300:48"/> then of Civill government,</hi> ſeeing that an <hi>Anarchie</hi> is the cauſe of all diſorder, &amp; confuſion in the ſtate. Inſomuch that the reaſon of al the ſinnes that were commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is often in the booke of Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges aſcribed vnto this, that they wanted a <hi>Magiſtrate: There was at that time no king in Iſrael.</hi> Iudg. 17. 6. 18. 1. 19. 1. 21. 25.</p>
            <p>It is a miſerable life, to liue vnder a <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> where nothing is lawfull; but farre worſe, to liue in an <hi>Anarchie</hi> where no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is vnlawfull. But I ſhall not need to trouble my ſelfe, or to tire out your atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by heaping vp multituds of reaſons for proving of this point, ſeeing it is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion ſo plainely averred by the holy Ghoſt:<note n="p" place="margin">Prov. 8.15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>by me kings reigne</hi> (ſaith the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God by the mouth of <hi>Solomon) &amp; princes decree iuſtice; by me princes rule, and the nobles, and all iudges of the earth.</hi> As if he had ſaid: it is not by the wit, and policie of man, that the government of ſtates is committed vnto kings, &amp; other inferiour Magiſtrats: it is effected by the wiſdome, and providence of God. With which the<note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> Apoſtle agreeth, when hee tels vs, that there is <hi>no power but of God, &amp; the powers that be, are ordeined of God.</hi> It
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:25300:49"/> was ſometime ſaid of<note n="r" place="margin">Dan. 5.19</note> 
               <hi>Nabuchadnezzar,</hi> that great king of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that <hi>whom hee would, he pulled downe, and whom he would, he ſet vp.</hi> But it is alwaies true of the king of heaven, who is
<q>—<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </q> the king of kings, and Lord of Lords; he pul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth down one, &amp; ſetteth vp an other, he diſpoſeth of their roomes, at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: For if<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pro. 21.1</note> 
               <hi>the harts of kings,</hi> much more their kingdomes, <hi>are at his diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> This is a truth to which the very heathen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues haue ſubſcribed. It was<note n="t" place="margin">2. Chr 9.8</note> God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone that did exalt <hi>Solomon</hi> vnto the throne of his father <hi>David,</hi> ſo the <hi>Queene</hi> of the <hi>South</hi> affirmed; that did exalt <hi>Cyrus</hi> to the kingdomes of the earth, ſo<note n="u" place="margin">2. Chr. 36 23.</note> he himſelfe confeſſed. Agreeing with that of the prophet<note n="a" place="margin">Pſ. 71.7.8</note> 
               <hi>David, Promotion comes not from the Eaſt, nor from the Weſt, no nor yet from the South. And why? God is the iudge, he putteth downe one, and ſetteth vp another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> 5 And is this true? Here then firſt the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> come to be cenſured, which withdraw their neckes from the yoke of civill governement, and condemne it, as not beſeeming the liberty of a Chriſtian
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:25300:49"/> man. A leſſon which they never learned from the prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> who foretolde, that in the time of the goſpell (an aſſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not away with; for though they graunt, that the <hi>Iewes,</hi> at Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, had their Magiſtrats, yet they thinke it not ſit for a Chriſtian to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to ſuch ſlavery) in the time I ſay of the goſpell he will appoint kings to bee patrons, &amp; propugnators of his Church.<note n="b" place="margin">Iſ. 49.23.</note> 
               <hi>Kings ſhall bee thy nurſing fathers and Queenes ſhall be thy nurces.</hi> Nor from our Saviour Chriſt, who though he told his diſciples,<note n="c" place="margin">Luk. 22.25.</note> when they ſtroue for ſuperio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity amongſt themſelues, that one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhoulde not domineere over another, as did the kings of the nations, yet it was ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver his meaning to withdraw them from obedience to ſuperiour governours, but that<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 22.21.</note> 
               <hi>Caeſar ſhould haue that which did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to Caeſar.</hi> Nor from<note n="e" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.17</note> 
               <hi>Peter,</hi> who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandes vs <hi>to honour the king.</hi> Nor from<note n="f" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> who commaundes vs to pray <hi>for kings, and all that are in autority, and that to this end, that we may lead a quiet, and peaceable life in all godlineſſe, and honeſtie.</hi> God knows better what is meet for chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> do. He knows
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:25300:50"/> that we are <hi>ſtrangers</hi> on earth, &amp; not <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> in heaven. And being<note n="g" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>ſtrangers and pilgrims,</hi> ſtand in as great need of theſe helps, as of fire, of water, of aire, of appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, of any thing, which is neceſſary for the ſuſtentation of our liues; ſeeing that they are not only the meanes that we are partakers of all theſe while they effect, that we may liue togither in civill ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but alſo the promoters of true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the adva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cers of vertue, the rewarders of piety, the puniſhers of ſin, the deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Idolatry, ſuperſtition, and al miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanours amongſt Chriſtians. So that as God ſaide vnto <hi>Samuel</hi> concerning the <hi>Iewes,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they diſliked their preſent go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,<note n="h" place="margin">1. Sam. 8.7.</note> 
               <hi>they haue not cast thee awaie, but they haue cast mee away, that I ſhoulde not reigne over them:</hi> ſo I may ſay of theſe fanaticall ſpirits, it is not the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> but God himſelfe, whom they haue reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that he ſhould not reigne over the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> 6 There is an other ſort of men, who, though not directly with the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> yet indirectly, &amp; by a conſequent, croſſe my propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I meane the <hi>Papists.</hi> Theſe doe not altogither take away the civill <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> but they tie his thummes &amp;
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:25300:50"/> abbridge his autority. It muſt be only <hi>in temporalibus:</hi> for ſpirituall matters, hee muſt haue no more dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <note n="i" place="margin">2. Sam. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vzza had to touch the arke of God.</hi> This they willingly grant, that the magiſtrats are <hi>Gods,</hi> but as the <hi>Aramits</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">1. King. 20.28.</note> that <hi>their Gods were Gods of the mountaines, &amp; not Gods of the vallies:</hi> ſo ſay they, the civill Magiſtrates, are <hi>Gods</hi> of the mountaines, and not <hi>Gods</hi> of the vallies; they are <hi>Gods</hi> of the <hi>Laity,</hi> but not of the <hi>Clergie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is naught in reſpect of that which followeth. For whereas God challengeth this as a prerogatiue vnto himſelfe, to be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtow kingdomes on whomſoever he wil, and placeth the Princes of the earth in authoritie next vnto himſelfe, this they haue perforce taken from God, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed it vpon him, that<note n="l" place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>ſitteth in the temple of God, and advanceth himſelfe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all that are called Gods.</hi> It is hee to whom (if yee will beleeue him, &amp; his <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſites</hi>) all <hi>power is committed, both in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and in earth.</hi> He is that <hi>King</hi> of <hi>kings,</hi> &amp; <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Lords,</hi> by whom Princes rule, and on whom the right of kings depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: all nations muſt fall downe before
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:25300:51"/> him, and al kingdomes muſt doe him ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. The greateſt <hi>Monarch</hi> of the earth muſt proſtrat himſelfe before him, &amp; kiſſe his holy feet. The <hi>Emperour,</hi> if he be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent when he taketh horſe, muſt hold the bridle, when hee lighteth, hee muſt hold the right ſtirrup, when hee walketh, hee muſt beare vp his traine, when hee waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, hee muſt hold the baſon, when hee would be borne, he muſt be one of the 4 that muſt carie him vpon their ſhoulders in a golden chaire.</p>
            <p n="7">7 And as hee takes vpon him to giue kingdomes to whomſoever he will (like the Divell, who told our Saviour Chriſt<note n="m" place="margin">Luk 4.6</note> that all the kingdomes of the world <hi>were his,</hi> and <hi>hee gaue them to whomſoever he would</hi> (wherevpon ſaith an ancient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note n="n" place="margin">Irenaeus.</note> 
               <hi>mentitur diabolus, quia cuius iuſſu homines creantur, huius iuſſu reges conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuuntur,</hi> the divell is a liar, for by whoſe autoritie men were created, by his are kings appointed) as he takes vpon him, I ſay, to giue kingdomes at his pleaſure, ſo wil he take them away when he liketh. So farre is he from that obedience, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which every ſoule ſhould giue to the higher power. Who knoweth not
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:25300:51"/> that<note n="o" place="margin">Chron. Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Leo Iſaurus</hi> for putting in executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a decree of a <hi>Councill</hi> held at <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> in his time, touching the taking away of images, was firſt excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, and then depriued of al his reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes in <hi>Italie?</hi> That Pope <hi>Zacharie</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed <hi>Childericke,</hi> the <hi>French king,</hi> that he might gratifie <hi>Carolus Mertellus,</hi> and his ſonne <hi>Pipin?</hi> That the proud <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> pedler,<note n="p" place="margin">Bonfin. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Vng. dec. <hi>4.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> the ſecond, by a publique edict depriued of crown and kingdome, <hi>George</hi> the <hi>king</hi> of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> becauſe hee was an <hi>Huſſite,</hi> &amp; ſtirred vp <hi>Mathias</hi> the king of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> (his ſon in law) to war againſt him? What ſhall I tell you of the indignities, offered in our owne land, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>ſecond,</hi> and <hi>Iohn, king</hi> of <hi>England?</hi> or of the buls of <hi>Pius Quintus,</hi> ſent againſt <hi>Queene Elizabeth</hi> of never dying memorie, whereby hee hath exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated her, abſolued her ſubiects, from their oaths of allegiance, ſtirred vp rebellions in theſe middle parts of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,</hi> and taken vpon him, to beſtow the regall diademe vpon ſtrangers. God bee thanked<note n="q" place="margin">Pſ. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>he that dwels in heaven</hi> (and, of right, challengeth the autoritie of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the kingdomes of this worlde
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:25300:52"/> to himſelfe) <hi>laughed all their deviſes to ſcorne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> So that his <hi>Canons,</hi> though they made a terrible noiſe, yet no bullet was felt. And his <hi>Bulls</hi> which ſometimes had ſuch a terrible aſpect, that a whole <hi>provinciall Synod</hi> durſt ſcarſe ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to baite them, proved ſuch coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly daſtards, that every ſingle adverſarie hath beene ready to tugge them. Much reſembling the counterfeite ſhews of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miramis,</hi> when ſhee warred againſt the king of <hi>India,</hi> which, a far off, ſeemed to be <hi>Elephants,</hi> &amp; <hi>Dromedaries,</hi> but when they were throughly tried, proved no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Oxen hides ſtuffed with ſtrawe.</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Apoc. 16.7.</note> 
               <hi>Even ſo Lorde God Almightie true and righteous are thy iudgementes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> That I may cut off this firſt bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch of my text: my third, &amp; laſt infere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cern you <hi>(R. H.)</hi> whom the Lord hath placed at the ſeat of iudgment. Haue <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> their authoritie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God? this concernes you in your places, as wel as the greateſt pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tate of the earth. And therfore as on the one ſide it ſhould be incouragment vnto you, to hold on in all godly courſes ye haue begunne; ſo on the other ſide, it ſhould worke in you, an humble, &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:25300:52"/> acknowledgement of ſo rare a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. Say not then within your ſelues, that it was your owne deſerts, the excellencie of your wits, the ripeneſſe of your iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the deepneſſe of your knowledge in the laws, the integrity of your perſons, that did adva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce you, vnto thoſe roomes: It was none of al theſe, it was God alone that did promote you. If theſe were meanes of your preferment, yet haue yee nothing whereof yee can iuſtly boaſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe yee haue them al from him. For <hi>Dei dona ſunt, quaecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> bona ſunt.</hi> Vſe then your places as received from him, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge God to be the author of your advancement, and ſay with<note n="ſ" place="margin">Luk 1.</note> 
               <hi>Mary</hi> in her <hi>Song: hee that is mighty hath done great things for vs, and holy is his name.</hi> And ſo much of the firſt propoſition. The ſecond followeth.</p>
            <q>Magiſtrates are Gods deputies.<note place="margin">2. Propoſ.</note>
            </q>
            <p n="8">8 God as he is iealous of his honour, ſo is he of his name too. He will not giue it vnto any other, but only ſo far as he hath ſome reſemblance with him. I finde only 3 in Gods booke, (to ſay nothing of that eternal eſſence, to which it principally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth) which haue this name given the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:25300:53"/> The firſt is <hi>Satan,</hi> who, by reaſon of his great, &amp; almoſt v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>limited power, which he hath for a time, here on earth, by ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling &amp; raigning in the hearts of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of diſobedience, is called a <hi>God. The God of this world,</hi> 2. Cor. 2.4. The ſecond are the bleſſed <hi>Angels,</hi> thoſe yeomen of the guard in the court of heaven, which wait about the throne of God. Theſe, by reaſon of their ſupereminent offices, are called <hi>Gods. Thou haſt made him a little inferiour to the Gods,</hi> Pſal. 8.5. which the Apoſtle, following the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlateth <hi>Angels,</hi> Heb. 2.7. The third, is the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> who, both in this Pſalme, &amp; ſundry other places of Scripture, is called a <hi>God. His maſter ſhall bring him to the Gods,</hi> Exod. 21.6. <hi>Thou ſhalt not rayle vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Gods,</hi> Exod. 22.28. that is, the <hi>Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges:</hi> implying thus much, that as they haue a commaundement, and autoritie from God; ſo they haue, in ſome ſenſe, the autoritie of God, and doe ſupply his roome. Therefore, ſaid <hi>Moſes</hi> vnto the Iudges which he appointed in every ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,<note n="t" place="margin">Deut. 1.36.</note> 
               <hi>ye ſhall not feare the face of man, for the iudgement is Gods.</hi> And <hi>Iehoſophat</hi> to thoſe Iudges, which hee had ſet in the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:25300:53"/> ſtrong cities of <hi>Iudah:</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">2. Chr. 19 6.</note> 
               <hi>take heed what you doe, for yee execute not the iudgement of man, but of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> 9 Now then, if Magiſtrates bee Gods deputies, what reverence, it behoueth each private perſon, to exhibit vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I appeale to the conſcience of every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular. There bee many at this day, who howſoever in common civilitie, they wil ſeeme to giue an outward reverence vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> yet in heart they ſcorn and contemne ſundry of them: as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance not being able to equalize them in wealth, peradventure not diſcending of ſo ancient a houſe as they.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Horat.</note>Tunè Syri, Damae, aut Dionyſi filius audes</l>
               <l>Deijcere e ſaxo cives, et tradere Cadmo?</l>
            </q>
            <p>It was an olde obiection in the <hi>Satyriſt:</hi> what? dareſt thou, being thus, &amp; thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended, preſume to giue iudgement vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a man that is better borne then thy ſelfe? yes; why not? hee is now in Gods place. <hi>Hee that lifteth the poore out of the myre, &amp; raiſeth the beggar out of the du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, that he may ſet him with the Princes of his people,</hi> hath ſtyled him, with his owne name, and ſet him in his roome. I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:25300:54"/> a ſtorie in<note n="b" place="margin">Herod. l. <hi>2</hi> Ariſt. polit. lib <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Herodotus,</hi> of <hi>Amaſis</hi> an <hi>Egyptian</hi> king, who, in the beginning of his reigne, was ſcorned of his ſubiects, by reaſon of the baſeneſſe of his parentage: which when the king obſerued, he tooke a <hi>golden baſen,</hi> wherein his gueſts were wont to waſh their feet, and vſe to ſome homely purpoſes, and thereof made an image of one of their Gods, and ſet it in an eminent place of the citie; which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Egyptians</hi> ſaw (as they were marvei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſuperſtitious) they came flocking on heapes vnto it, &amp; worſhipped it. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon <hi>Amaſis,</hi> calling the people toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, told the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that hee was like vnto that baſen, which before was vile and abiect, yet now was worſhipped, becauſe of the forme it bare: ſo hee, though before hee was meane, and baſe, yet now was to bee honoured, becauſe he was the <hi>king,</hi> for the perſons ſake whom he did repreſent. It skilleth not, what the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> hath beene, or what hereafter he may be. For the preſent, bee thy reputation never ſo great, thou art to honour and reverence him, if not for the mans ſake, yet for Gods ſake, whoſe perſon he beareth. The ſtory of<note n="c" place="margin">Liv. dec. <hi>3.</hi> lib <hi>4.</hi> Plu<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in vit. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bii.</note> 
               <hi>Quintus Fabius</hi> is very worthie the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:25300:54"/> noting. <hi>Quintus Fabius</hi> was ſent by the <hi>Senate</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> to his ſonne, who was <hi>Conſul,</hi> and reſided at that time in <hi>Apu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia.</hi> The old man, either by reaſon of his age, or to trie his ſonnes courage, went riding to his ſonne: which when his ſon obſerued, hee ſent a Sergeant, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to light, and come on foot, if he would ſpeake with the <hi>Conſul.</hi> The by-ſtanders thought it great arrogancie in the young man to be ſo bold with his aged father. But old <hi>Fabius,</hi> who had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, what it was to be <hi>Conſul,</hi> knew well, that hee did no more then did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeme him: <hi>experiri volui fili</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin' ſcires Conſulem te eſſe.</hi> It is not for a <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> to debaſe himſelfe: neither is it for others, of what reputation ſoever, to equalize themſelues with the <hi>Iudge</hi> whom God hath placed over the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: whom <hi>Solomon</hi> would <hi>haue to be feared;</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Prov. 24.21.</note> whom<note n="*" place="margin">Pet. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>Peter would haue to be honoured;</hi> whom<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 13.5.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> would <hi>haue to bee obeyed, not for wrath only, but even for conſcience ſak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 And this is not only meant of godly and religious <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> ſuch as are deſcribed by<note n="g" place="margin">Deut 17.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> which make Gods law of their privie <hi>Counſell,</hi> and turne not
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:25300:55"/> aſide to the right hand, or to the left: but of wicked and vngodly governours too; ſuch as are deſcribed by<note n="h" place="margin">1 Sam. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Samuel,</hi> which take mens <hi>ſons, &amp; appoint them to his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets, &amp; to be his horſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; to ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before his charets, &amp; take their fields, &amp; giue them to his ſervaunts, and their vineyards, and giue them to his Eunuches.</hi> The reaſon, is, becauſe as wel the badde, as the good <hi>are of God.</hi> The one he giues in his loue the other in his anger. Hee that gaue the regiment of a Commonwealth to <hi>Caius Caeſar,</hi> a milde, and gentle Prince, gaue it alſo vnto <hi>Marius</hi> a bloody <hi>Conſul.</hi> Hee that gaue it vnto <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> a myrrour of humanitie, gaue it vnto <hi>Nero,</hi> a monſter of crudelitie. Hee that gaue it vnto <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſian,</hi> gaue it vnto <hi>Domitian.</hi> Hee that gaue it vnto <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> a religious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of Chriſtianity, gaue it vnto <hi>Iulia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> an authour of apoſtaſie, ſaith<note n="i" place="margin">Auguſt. de Civil Dei lib <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>21</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtine.</hi> And bee they good or bad, wee haue no commandment from him, but <hi>parendi, &amp; patiendi:</hi> of obeying them, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts are not repugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to Gods ſtatutes, and of ſuffering with patience whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they ſhall lay vpon vs. It was a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie ſaying of the mother of the two<note n="k" place="margin">Bonſin. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Vag. dec. <hi>3.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Garaes,</hi> when they kept <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> in
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:25300:55"/> priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that <hi>a crowned king, if he were worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a beaſt, could not be hurt without great iniurie done to God himſelfe.</hi> A leſſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſhe learned from<note n="l" place="margin">1. Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 24</note> 
               <hi>David,</hi> whoſe hearte ſmote him, when hee had cut the <hi>lappe of Sauls garment,</hi> becauſe he was the anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Lord: although hee<note n="m" place="margin">1. Sam. 13 14.</note> himſelfe was before that time anointed to be king over <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and was without cauſe, hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Saul</hi> like a <hi>Pelican in the wildernes, and an owle in the deſart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11 Then to draw thy ſword, &amp; to ſeek perforce to depoſe ſuch as God hath pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced over thee, either becauſe they are not ſutable to thy affections, or not faithfull in their places, what is it but, with the old <hi>gyants,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to fight with God: with the curre dog, to bite at the ſtone, &amp; not regard who caſteth it: or, with the rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious child, to ſnatch at the rodde, &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver remember who ſmiten with it. The weapons of a Chriſtian, in this caſe (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch a caſe doth happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) muſt be <hi>preces &amp; lacrymae, prayers,</hi> that either God would turne the heart of an evill <hi>magiſtrate,</hi> or ſet in his roome a man<note n="n" place="margin">1. Sam. 13 14.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi>-like after his owne heart: and <hi>teares,</hi> for his ſinnes, which as they are the cauſe of warre, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:25300:56"/> peſtilence, and all other calamities, ſo are they alſo of wicked &amp; vngodly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates. Otherwiſe they haue reaſon to feare, that, if God ſhould diſplace an evil <hi>magiſtrate,</hi> he would ſett a worſe in his roo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. According to that of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Val Max. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> old wife of <hi>Syracuſe,</hi> who when others praied for the death of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the <hi>Tyrant,</hi> ſhee prayed for his long life, being ſent for by <hi>Dyonyſius,</hi> &amp; demaunded wherin ſhe was beholden vnto him, that ſhe ſo devoutly prayed for him: in nothing, ſaid ſhe, am I beholden to thee, &amp; yet I haue great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to pray for thee. For I remember whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I was a yong wench, there was a cruel ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that reigned over vs; and all of vs prayd for his death, I as faſt as any: ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after he was ſlayne, and then came a worſe in his roome. Then we prayed for his death, at length he was diſpatched. Now after both theſe art thou come, and thou art a thouſand times worſe then all thy predeceſſours. And who knowes but, when thou art gone, God may (if it bee poſſible) ſend a worſe in thy roome? This they may iuſtly expect, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in their ſinnes, &amp; think by their private en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to croſſe Gods ordinance. Thus
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:25300:56"/> much of thoſe duties, which are required at the hand of every private man towards the <hi>Magiſtrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> 12 My ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d inference ſhal touch thoſe duties that are required at the hands of <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> in that God hath made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his deputies. As God hath done great things for them, ſo he requireth much at their hands. But (alas) it often falleth out that thoſe which owe God the moſt, pay him the leaſt: and thoſe, who of al others ſhould be moſt carefull of their places, of al others make the leaſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience of their waies.<note n="p" place="margin">Annal. l. <hi>6</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tacitus</hi> reporteth of <hi>Claudius</hi> that he was a <hi>good ſubiect, but an ill Emperour:</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Hiſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>Titus,</hi> that he was <hi>an ill ſubiect, but a good Emperour.</hi> Where one proues like <hi>Titus;</hi> two proue like <hi>Claudius. Honours change manners.</hi> And thoſe goodly bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes, which did appeare in many when they were private men, when they come in Gods place, like froſt-eaten buds, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther away, &amp; proue like thunder-blaſted fruit, not worth the touching, much leſſe the taſting. It is noted of<note n="r" place="margin">Buchc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c. Ind. Chron.</note> 
               <hi>Aeneas Syluius,</hi> that when once he became <hi>Pope,</hi> and got his name changed into <hi>Pius ſecundus,</hi> he condemned divers of thoſe things which
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:25300:57"/> he had written, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was a private ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Whervpon one came over him with this quippe, <hi>quod Aeneas probavit, Pius dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>navit:</hi> that which <hi>Aeneas</hi> commended, <hi>Pius</hi> condemned. A fault to which men of eminent place are too much ſubiect, to condemne and diſlike thoſe good things when they are in autority, which they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved when they were privat men. <hi>Quod Aeneas probavit, Pius damnabit.</hi> Thus, thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God cals <hi>Elohim,</hi> change their natures, and proue <hi>Elilim</hi> idols, and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. The heathen perſecuters (as<note n="f" place="margin">Abbas Viſp.</note> ſome writers haue recorded) in the place where Chriſt was crucified had placed the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus,</hi> a heathen idoll, that if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhould worſhip Chriſt, he might ſeem to adore <hi>Venus.</hi> This is the devils practiſe, to ſet an idoll in Gods roome; ſometimes a <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus,</hi> a <hi>Cupid,</hi> that vſe their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for the enioying of their owne carnal pleaſures; ſometimes a <hi>Mars,</hi> vſing his power to blood and revenge; ſometimes a <hi>Saturne,</hi> that eateth vp his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (that is, his inferiours, which he ſhould affect as a father doth his own children) as if they were bread; ſometimes a <hi>Mercurie,</hi> who is eloquent in ſpeaking, but withall nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:25300:57"/> in fingring, having a ſmooth tongue like <hi>Iacob,</hi> but rough hands like <hi>Eſau,</hi> nay Eagle clawes like <hi>Nabuchadnezzar,</hi> to ſcrape, and ſcratch togither whatſoever comes in his way, vſing his place only for his owne advantage. Here is the vndoing of all: for, beſides that Gods place is pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, and the people wronged, there is an evill preſident given to private me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the wicked example of their gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours. For as the lower <hi>ſpheres,</hi> follow the motion of the higher: ſo in the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, thoſe that are of an inferior ranke are ready to follow the practiſe of thoſe that are ſet over them. When a ſhrub, or bramble falleth, they hurt none but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; but when a <hi>Cedar</hi> of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> or an oke of <hi>Baſan</hi> falleth, down goes al the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-wood that grows about the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It is the nature of the plague to infect vpwards, from a lower, to a higher roome: but the plague of ſin is more forcible in infecting downewards, from an higher, to a lower room. It diſcends fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the top to the toe &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the head to the skirts of the clothing. If<note n="t" place="margin">Mat. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>Herod</hi> be troubled about the birth of Chriſt, all Ieruſalem will be in an vproare with him. And if<note n="u" place="margin">1. Kin. 12</note> 
               <hi>Ieroboam</hi> be an idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<q>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:25300:58"/>
                  <l>—<note n="a" place="margin">Claud.</note> componitur orbis</l>
                  <l>Regis ad exemplum:</l>
               </q> all <hi>Iſrael</hi> wil go a whoring after him. And herevpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is, that yee ſhall ſeldome meet with his name in the books of Kings, but you ſhall finde him branded in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head with this marke, that <hi>he made Iſrael to ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13 God be thanked, wee haue no great occaſion of complaint at this day; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in our chiefe <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> (&amp; I wiſh, I might without checke of conſcience ſay as much of thoſe, that are of an inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ranke) The Lord hath ſet over vs (his name for ever bee bleſſed for it) a moſt godly and religious <hi>King,</hi> of whom (as<note n="b" place="margin">Rarâ tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citate, vbi ſentire qua velis &amp; quae ſentis dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re licet Hiſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tacitus</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aith of <hi>Traiane,</hi> and <hi>Cocceius Nerva</hi>) a man may thinke what he wil, &amp; ſpeake what he thinkes. God hath giuen him (as hee did vnto<note n="c" place="margin">1. King. 4 29.</note> 
               <hi>Solomon) a large heart as the ſand that is vpon the ſea ſhoare</hi> to iudge his people according to right, and to<note n="d" place="margin">1. Kin. 3 9</note> 
               <hi>diſcerne betweene good and bad.</hi> Whoſe princely care is to obſerue the practiſe of the olde <hi>Romanes,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Auguſt. de Civ. Dei l. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>12,</hi>
               </note> to ſet <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors temple</hi> cloſe on the backſide of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues temple</hi> and not wittingly to ſuffer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to come into the <hi>Temple of Honour,</hi>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:25300:58"/> which haue not firſt done their devotion in the <hi>Temple of Vertue:</hi> not to make his Iudges, and chiefe <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> (like <hi rend="sup">f</hi> 
               <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboams</hi> Prieſts) of the baſeſt,<note n="e" place="margin">1 Kin. 12.31.</note> &amp; loweſt of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e people; but ſuch as<note n="g" place="margin">Eood. 18.21.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> at <hi>Iethro's</hi> perſwaſion, made Iudges over <hi>Iſrael, men of courage, fearing God, men dealing truly, and hating covetouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14 And ſuch <hi>(R. H.)</hi> you haue by good demonſtrations evidently proued your ſelues to bee. So that to make any large diſcourſe before you, of your particular duties, may pervadventure ſeeme vnto ſome, as needleſſe a peece of work, as it was for<note n="h" place="margin">Tull. de orat. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmio,</hi> to make a military diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe before <hi>Annibal;</hi> or for <hi>Plotin</hi> to read a lecture in Philoſophie in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of <hi>Origen.</hi> Yet becauſe it comes within the limits of my text, I beſeech you that you, wil with patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce heare me, while I ſhall ſay ſomewhat of that dutie which God requires at your hands, in that hee hath ſeated you in thoſe high roomes. Many will tell you of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of your places; but not ſo many will truly acquaint you with that which God requires for the diſcharging of thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. For my part me thinkes I may ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:25300:59"/> you, as<note n="i" place="margin">Liv. dec. <hi>1.</hi> lib. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lucius Poſthumius</hi> ſometimes ſaid vnto the <hi>Senatours</hi> of <hi>Rome: Non ſum Patres-conſcripti adeò veſtrae dignitatis memor, vt obliviſcar me eſſe Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſulem.</hi> I am not ſo mindfull of the greatneſſe of your places, that I ſhould in the meane time forget mine owne, how that God hath made me his Ambaſſadour, &amp; comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded mee to acquaint you with ſome part of his will.</p>
            <p n="15">15 It is our parts, &amp; duties, to giue you that reverence, and honour, which is due vnto men of your place. But yet as the people ſaid vnto the <hi>Aſſe</hi> that caried the image of <hi>Iſis,</hi> when the beaſt ſeemed to be proud, becauſe the people bowed as it went along the ſtreets, as if the honour had beene giuen vnto it, and not vnto the image: <hi>religioni no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tibi,</hi> ſaid they, it is not thee, but the goddeſſe, whom wee wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. So it is not to you as yee are men, but as you are in Gods place, &amp; do beare, and reſemble his perſon, that we exhibit this reverence. <hi>You are Gods,</hi> but yee are <hi>Gods</hi> on earth, and <hi>Gods</hi> of earth, as wee ſhall heare anon. Mathematitians tell vs, that the whole earth is but a point in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the higheſt moueable: it is no
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:25300:59"/> more in reſpect of that heaven, which is Gods throne, then<note n="k" place="margin">Aelian. Var. hiſt. l. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Alcibiades</hi> his lands were in that mappe of <hi>Greece</hi> that <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> ſhewed vnto him. The greateſt Iudge in the world, if his circuit ſhould extende over the whole globe of the earth, is but a <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> footſtoole. Your circuit is farre leſſe: you are but <hi>Gods</hi> of an outcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, nay, a little portion of an out-corner of <hi>Gods</hi> footſtoole. Let mee then ſpeake vnto you in the words of the <hi>Tragoedian,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>os, quibus rector maris,<note n="l" place="margin">Seneca in Thyeſte.</note> at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> terrae</l>
                  <l>Ius dedit magnum necis, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vitae,</l>
                  <l>Ponite inſlatos tumidoſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vultus,</l>
               </q> you whom the <hi>God</hi> of heaven, and earth hath ſo highly extolled, as to make Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of life and death, bee not proud of your autorities, but thinke with your ſelues, that,
<q>
                  <l>Quicquid à vobis minor extimeſcit,</l>
                  <l>Maior hoc vobis Dominus minatur.</l>
               </q> What hurt ſoever your inferiours ſhall ſuſtaine by your meanes, there is a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God, that threatneth the ſame (nay a worſe) vnto you.<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Be wiſe now therefore O yee Gods: be learned yee that are Iudges of the earth: ſerue the Lord with feare, and reioice before him with trembling: kiſſe the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:25300:60"/> ſonne, least he be angry.</hi> Let his word be a law to direct your ſentences, his will the line to meaſure your actions. With what conſcience can thoſe hands ſubſcribe to an vntruth, which ſhould be Gods inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to confirme a right? with what fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces can thoſe mouthes pronounce an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which ſhould be the organes of God to confirme a right? When you do amiſſe, you are not only iniurious vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man whom yee wrong, but contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious vnto God, whoſe ſacred iudgments yee pollute. Giue mee leaue then to ſay vnto you with good king<note n="n" place="margin">2. Chr. 19 6, 7.10.</note> 
               <hi>Iehoſophat: take heed what yee doe, for yee execute not the iudgements of man, but of the Lord, &amp; he will be with you in the cauſe, and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Wherefore now let the feare of God be vpon you; take heed and doe it: for there is no iniquitie in the Lord our God, neither respect of perſons, nor receauing of reward. Therefore in every cauſe that ſhall come vnto you, between blood and blood, between law and precept, statute and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udgement, yee ſhall iudge the people according vnto right, and admoniſh them that they trespaſſe not againſt the Lord.</hi> Let me ſay with<note n="o" place="margin">Deut. 1.16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes, Iudge righteouſly betweene every man, and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:25300:60"/> his brother, and the ſtranger that is with him: yee ſhall haue no respect of perſons in iudgement, but ſhall heare the ſmall, as well as the great.</hi> With<note n="p" place="margin">Ier. 22.3.</note> 
               <hi>Ieremiah</hi> vnto the king of <hi>Iudah: Execute iudgement and righteouſneſſe, deliver the oppreſſed from the handes of the oppreſſour, vexe not the ſtranger, the fatherleſſe, nor the widow, doe no violence, nor ſhed innocent blood in this place.</hi> And finally with my <hi>Prophet</hi> in this Pſalme: <hi>Defend the poore and fatherleſſe, ſee that ſuch as be in need, &amp; neceſſity haue right, deliver the outcaſt, and poore, ſaue them from the hands of the vngodly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16 I ſpeake not this, as if I would haue you to exceed the limits of iuſtice, for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſerating the cauſe of the poore. I know the poore may offend as well as the rich: &amp; as the poore is to be pitied, ſo the rich is not to be wronged. And he that hath given this law vnto the Magiſtrate, that he ſhould not <hi>reſpect the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie,</hi> hath giuen this alſo,<note n="q" place="margin">Lev. 19.15</note> that he ſhould <hi>not favour the perſon of the poore.</hi> It is not the miſerie of the one, nor the felicitie of the other, that the Iudge is to reſpect. For the matters in queſtion, ſound them to the bottome, anatomize them to the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:25300:61"/> leaſt particle, and ſift them to the branne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but for the parties whom they doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne, further then this, that yee are to iudge betweene a man and a man, yee ought not to enquire. The<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>lawe</hi> in the Greeke tongue comes from a <hi>verbe</hi> that ſignifieth to <hi>divide,</hi> becauſe it divideth to every man, that which is his own. You then which are diſpenſers of the lawe ſhould giue to every one, poore or rich, that which is his right. Herevpon it is that<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ariſt. Eth. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> cals the Iudge in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutatiue iuſtice <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or as ſome co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies haue it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>medianus,</hi> or <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurius,</hi> a meane betweene two; becauſe he ſhould not propend to the one partie, more then the other, but only ſo farre as the weight of the cauſe carieth him, and ſhould giue to every man that which is his right, and that not according to <hi>geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metricall,</hi> but according to <hi>arithmeticall</hi> proportion: that is, not with <hi>Xenophons</hi> young <hi>Cyrus</hi> giue the greater coat vnto the greater man, and the leſſer coate vnto the leſſer man, but to giue the greater coat (if it be his due) vnto the leſſer man, and let the greater man (if hee haue right to no more) be contented with the leſſer coat.</p>
            <p n="17">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:25300:61"/>17 But the principall thing, which it beſeemeth me to put you in mind of, and which is chiefly required at your hands, as yee are factors for the God of heaven, is the care of religion, and the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God. Nothing is ſo deare vnto God, as his owne worſhip. He that tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth it, woundes him to the heart, and pearceth the apple of his eie. It is an iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie which he will not put vp at the hands of any man, but will come againſt him, as <hi>the fire that burneth vp the ſtubble, and as the hammer that breaketh a ſtone.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it moſt neerly concerneth you, who are his deputies, to maintaine his ſervice, and to put what ſtrength you can vnto the hammer of iuſtice, that yee may (as far as the lawes will giue you leaue) burſt into peeces, whatſoever ſhall advance it ſelfe againſt his worſhip.</p>
            <p n="18">18 The ſickneſſes in religion, that are amongſt vs, are not <hi>Novatianiſme, Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, Cathariſme.</hi> No, no: theſe hot <hi>phre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zies</hi> are ſcarſe heard of in this cold climat wherein we liue. They are cold <hi>Epilepſies</hi> and dead <hi>Apoplexies,</hi> and ſleepy <hi>Lethar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies,</hi> &amp; dangerous <hi>Conſumptions,</hi> that vex vs. The main root, whence they al ſpring,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:25300:62"/> is a diſeaſe, with which this lande is ſicke. And that is the bold profeſſion of Popery: for hereby the true Chriſtians are mightily diſcouraged, thoſe that are infected with <hi>Romiſh</hi> ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, by little and little, to fall away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs; The ignorant are doubtfull, &amp; knowe not what to do, but are ready to embrace any religion, or no religion, as time and occaſion ſhall require; The <hi>Atheiſt</hi> (a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine wherewith this whole countrey ſwarmes, though they cannot be well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, by reaſon that they weare vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards vpon their faces) is hardned and heartned in his impietie.</p>
            <p>For vs, we doe what wee can to cut in ſunder this bitter root. Gladly <hi>would wee heale them of Babylon, but they will not bee healed.</hi> For our private conferences with any of them, if they want wit to anſwere our reaſons, they haue will to let them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. For our publike worke of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, leaſt we ſhould catch ſome of them they will not come within the compaſſe of our nets. The laſt weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the church is <hi>fulmen excommunicationis,</hi> to driue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of our <hi>Synagogues.</hi> And what care they for this, who wil not come in them,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:25300:62"/> no, when we doe entreat them? they cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it but <hi>brutum fulmen,</hi> a thunder clap, with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out a bolt, a canon-ſhot without a bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let: it hurts them no more then the dart which old <hi>Priamus</hi> in the<note n="t" place="margin">Virg Aen. li. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Poet</hi> ſhot at <hi>Pyrrhus:</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>— Quod protinus aere repulſum,</l>
                  <l>In ſummo clypei, nequidquam vmbone pependit.</l>
               </q> Further then this we cannot go: the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of our warfare are ſpirituall. Coac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue iuriſdiction is beyond our ſpheare. what is now behind? <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi deſinit Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus, incipiat medicus;</hi> where the word leaues them, let the ſword find them. <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chium ſeculare,</hi> was the help, &amp; aſſiſtance that the holy fathers of the <hi>Councill</hi> of <hi>Conſtance</hi> implored againſt the poore <hi>Huſſites.</hi> And <hi>brachium ſeculare</hi> is the helpe and aſſiſtance, that wee implore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe <hi>Cananites,</hi> that are amongſt vs. Which (howſoever vnto the <hi>halting Mephiboſheths,</hi> and <hi>lukewarme Laodice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> of our time, which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blow both cold and hot out of the ſame mouth: &amp; weare linnen and wollen in the ſame garment, and yoke an oxe, and an aſſe in the ſame plowe, &amp; care not if their fields be ſowne
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:25300:63"/> with mingled ſeedes, they bee never a whit noyſome: yet vnto the true <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite,</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Num. 33.55.</note> 
               <hi>they are thorns in his ſides &amp; pricks in his eies;</hi> and giues him iuſt occaſion to exhibit that bill of complaint againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which the <hi>Iews</hi> framed moſt falſly againſt the<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 21.28</note> 
               <hi>Apoſtle, yee men of Iſrael</hi> (nay yee Gods of <hi>Iſrael) helpe, theſe are the men that teach all men every where, againſt the people, and the law, and this place.</hi> Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they haue brought (not <hi>Grecians,</hi> as it is in the text, but a more peſtilent ſect) <hi>Romans into the land, and haue polluted this holy place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19 I ſpeake not only of thoſe children of <hi>Babylon,</hi> thoſe ſonnes of <hi>Belial,</hi> the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of the beaſt, the viperous brood of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Seminary Prieſts &amp; Ieſuites, that crawle in every quarter of this land, like <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 8.</note> 
               <hi>frogs of Egypt;</hi> and<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 23 15</note> 
               <hi>travel ſea &amp; land, to make one of their owne profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he may be twofold more the child of the devill, then they themſelues are:</hi> but alſo of theſe limmes of Antichriſt, theſe factors, and panders for the great whore, that are at home, &amp; ſit vnder their own fig trees, &amp; drinke the water of their own ceſterns.<note n="d" place="margin">Cic. <hi>2.</hi> Cal.</note> 
               <hi>Quos video volitare in foro, quos ſtare ad
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:25300:63"/> curiam, quos etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> venire in ſenatum,</hi> as the Orator ſpeaks. Theſe, theſe are <hi>noſtri fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di calamitas,</hi> the very moths of our regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; the cankarwormes of our religion. <hi>Wherefore gird you with your ſwords,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Pſ. 45.4.</note> 
               <hi>vpon your thighes, &amp; be not faint harted</hi> (like<note n="f" place="margin">Iud. 8.20.</note> 
               <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther</hi> the firſt borne of <hi>Gedeon) but let your right hand teach you terrible things.</hi> No doubt but they wil complaine of cruelty, &amp; perſecution (they do that already, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue no cauſe) but let not that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage you, but rather let it be a means that they may haue the ſame law, which the old<note n="g" place="margin">Tull. pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Roſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Capitolian dogs</hi> had: when they barked without a cauſe, their legs were to be broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If the differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce between the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and vs, be <hi>de lanâ caprinâ,</hi> about toyes &amp; triſles, let them be aſhamed of their bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy cruelty, that haue butchered, &amp; maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſo many thouſands of our brethren, for toies and trifles. Yea, &amp; let vs be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med likewiſe, that haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued ſo long in ſchiſme, &amp; diviſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> church for matters of ſo ſmal moment. If they be (as I take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be) fundame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal points of Chriſtianity, (alas) what worldly reſpect ſhal be ſufficient to coole the heat of our zeale in Gods cauſe? If our religion be a
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:25300:64"/> new religion, &amp; theirs the old, &amp; Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, let vs forſake our new-fangles, &amp; ioine with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The old, is the true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If ours be the old, &amp; Catholique reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which the <hi>Apostles</hi> haue taught vs, the martyrs haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed vnto vs, &amp; the faithfull till this day haue mainetained &amp; taught: &amp; theirs a new and an vpſtar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion an hotch-potch &amp; <hi>Pandora</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of al religions in the world, ſcarce heard off (for any material point of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between them &amp; vs) in the church of God, for ſixe hundreth yeares after Chriſt: let them pare away theſe rotten rags, theſe<note n="h" place="margin">Iſ 64.6.</note> 
               <hi>filthy</hi> and <hi>menſtruous clouts,</hi> and<note n="i" place="margin">Gal. 4.9.</note> 
               <hi>beggarly rudiments,</hi> &amp; let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ioine with vs. Either let vs all ſweare by <hi>God</hi> or all by<note n="k" place="margin">Zeph. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>Malcham.</hi> Either let vs all ſerue <hi>God,</hi> or all <hi>Baal;</hi> if God be <hi>God,</hi> let vs all follow him, if <hi>Baal</hi> be <hi>God,</hi> let vs al go af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him.</p>
            <p n="20">20 I know what ſome will be ready to anſwere me, though in matters of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be different from vs, yet for civil du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties they will bee ſubiects good enough. You ſay true, ſir, and ſo the kite will be a doue good enough: but wote yee when? marry<note n="l" place="margin">Iſto pacto &amp; milv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s quando pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los rapere ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritus non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuerit co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum ſe nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. Aug. con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tra lit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etil. lib <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>83.</hi>
               </note> when he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſeaze vpon a chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:25300:64"/> and make her his pray, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeakes. Is it likely that he will be true to an earthly king, that in matters of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is his oppoſite, who is falſe to the king of heaven? Philoſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers, though they hold that it is not the ſame vertue that makes <hi>bonum virum,</hi> &amp; <hi>bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cive<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> yet the beſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agree in this principle, that he cannot be <hi>bonus civis,</hi> good in the duties of civil policy, which is not firſt <hi>bonus vir,</hi> perfect in the general duties of morality: neither can he be true in practiſing the virtues of the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d table, which is falſe in the firſt. Doſt thou think, that the oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is a band of ſufficient force to tie a Papiſt in true allegiance vnto his prince?</p>
            <q>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Horat.</note>Quo teneas vultum mutantem Protea nodo?</q>
            <p>Canſt thou binde <hi>Proteus,</hi> that turns him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into every ſhape? Or canſt thou make a coate for the moone, that is never at a ſtay? Was there ever oath ſo wiſely contrived, ſo religiouſly taken, but the ſlippery ſnakes, and ſtretching horſelea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>Rome,</hi> could finde ſome chinke to creepe out at? or their Holy Father, out of his <hi>Papal,</hi> and tranſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dent power can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with it, or cut it, as<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Alexander</hi> did
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:25300:65"/> 
               <hi>Gordians</hi> knot, or breake it, as<note n="o" place="margin">Iud. 16.12</note> 
               <hi>Sampſon</hi> did the new ropes, wherewith the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> had bound him, which he brake fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his armes, as a threed?</p>
            <p n="21">21 Verily I think there is no probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to be a true Papiſt, &amp; a true ſubiect. A few ſimple ſeduced creatures amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs, that vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not the myſteries of pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but only in a generality, I ſpeak not of them: (and yet I know how eaſilie the yong <hi>cubbes</hi> may be taught to learne the tricks of the old <hi>Foxes</hi>) but for the reſt, the time paſt wil helpe vs to diſcover the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the time to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. To ſay nothing of their da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable, &amp; treacherous practiſes a broad againſt forreine princes, &amp; here at home againſt <hi>Queene Elizabeth</hi> of never dying memory, and the breath of our noſtrils <hi>King Iames;</hi> that one gunpowder-plot, a deviſe ſet from the bottome of hell, may be an everlaſting <hi>memento</hi> of their diſloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie,
<q>
                  <l>Accipe nunc Danaúm inſidias, &amp; crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ab vno</l>
                  <l>Diſce omnes—</l>
               </q> By this one fact wee may iudge of all the reſt, as an aſſe may be known by his long eares, &amp; as the bignes of <hi>Hercules</hi> might
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:25300:65"/> be gathered by the print of his foot. And though<note n="p" place="margin">P. R.</note> ſome of them, to make it leſſe hainous, call it <hi>a particular fact</hi> of a few, and that <hi>temerarious</hi> too, as though, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, it had been farre from their hearts to haue attempted any ſuch cruelty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lords annointed: yet it may be truely ſaid of them al, as <hi>Tullie</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Catilinarians, alijs facultas defuit, alijs oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſio, volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tas profectò nemini.</hi> And he, that in outward ſhew ſeemes moſt againſt it, would haue lent both heart, and hand, &amp; put to the very match, ſo that he might haue effected that matchleſſe treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And why ſhould it be otherwiſe? For what, I pray you, is any Prince in the world, if he doe not adhere to the Apoſtaticall <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Rome?</hi> ſhall I define him vnto you out of their Logique books?<note n="q" place="margin">Bell. Sand. Creſwell. Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cherius. Rainolds.</note> 
               <hi>A wolfe devouring the ſheepe; an Ahab or Iezabel, deſtroying the Lords Prophets; an Holofernes,</hi> a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed enimy to the true <hi>Iſraelite; a Goli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah, reviling the hoaſt of the living God;</hi> a <hi>ſeducer, and deceiver</hi> of the people, as our Saviour was called by their old gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers. And muſt not ſuch a one be made away by one meanes or other, by open hoſtility, or ſecret conſpiracy, it makes
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:25300:66"/> no matter?</p>
            <q>—dolus an virtus quis in hoste requirit?</q>
            <p>Shall not the ſhepheard do well to kill a wolfe? ſhall not<note n="r" place="margin">Iud. 13.8.</note> 
               <hi>Iudeth</hi> be highly extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led if ſhe can kill <hi>Holofernes</hi> though ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in his bed? And if<note n="ſ" place="margin">Sam. 18.7</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> kill <hi>Goli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> deſerues he not to be met with the wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> with timbrels, and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ioy, ſinging thus, <hi>Saul hath kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his thouſand, but David his ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand?</hi> In a word, is it not their aſſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that <hi>Princes muſt not be ſuffered to reigne, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they draw the people into hereſie, but muſt be made away, yea by all meanes poſſible.</hi> And therefore I leſſe marveile, why that reviling <hi>Rabſhekeh,</hi> that braſen-faced fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitiue <hi>Parſons,</hi> who bluſht not to ſay any thing in his yonger yeares, in his old age tooke vpon him a kinde of modeſty, and durſt promiſe no more for his fellowes then this; that <hi>there was no impoſſibility for Papiſts to liue in ſubiection, and dutifull o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience vnto the king of great Britaine.</hi> For poſſibility it is not the queſtion, but for probability it is no more, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the winde, and the ſea, light, and darknes, the Arke and Dagon, God, and Mammo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the vnbeleever and the infidell ſhall be togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:25300:66"/> For what I pray you is it, which knits me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as it were with chaines of ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in loue amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, &amp; in loial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and obedience vnto their Prince? Is it feare of puniſhment? Oh no, for <hi>malus est cuſtos diuturnitatis metus.</hi> Hee never reignes long, whom every man feareth; <hi>Cave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> multos, quem time<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſinguli,</hi> let him beware of a multitude whom every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dreadeth. Is it hope of rewarde? not that neither. For that is often fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and then followeth an alteration in the affections. It is neither of theſe. It is religion and the true feare of God. This, this is it which knits the <hi>heterogeneall</hi> parts, of the ſame kingdome vnto the prince, as the ſeverall parts of mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die are by arteries knit, and vnited vnto the heart, and as the lines of a circle, though they be far diſtant about the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference, yet concurre in one middle point: ſo muſt it be with them. Though they be different about the circumfere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of worldly affaires, yet muſt they concur in one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon center of religion. A good Chriſtian commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>wealth is likevnto<note n="t" place="margin">Act. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> ſheet, wherein were al <hi>maner of foure footed beaſts, and creeping things, &amp; fowles
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:25300:67"/> of the heaven.</hi> There are in it all ſortes of men. There are nobles flying aloft, like the fowles of the heaven; there are of the baſer ſort, creeping as it were below; and there are of a middle ſort, men of all conditions, and callings. But this ſheet is knit togither (as that was) at the 4 cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners (the moſt diſtant and remote parts thereof) with the vnitie of religion.</p>
            <p n="22">22 This is ſo plain, that<note n="u" place="margin">Ariſt. Pol. lib. <hi>5</hi> cap. <hi>11</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> giues it as an eſpeciall rule for a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> if hee meane to continue his government, to make an outward ſhew of religion. For ſuch kings (ſaith he) as ſeeme to bee reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, are in leaſt danger of treacherous practiſes by ſuch as are vnder them. Now where this vnitie of religion is wanting, (as wanting it is, ſeeing we differ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Papiſts, not in a few circumſtances, but in ſundry fundamental points of Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) how can this knot be made faſt? Nay, ſeeing they are ſo farre from counting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Proteſtant Prince religious, that they count him an hereticke; and the more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent he is, in clenſing and refining his kingdome from the dregges of <hi>Romiſh</hi> ſuperſtition (as our Saviour Chriſt was in purging the law from the abſurd gloſſes
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:25300:67"/> of the Scribes and Phariſees) the greater perſecuter he is holden with them to bee of the Catholike faith. Verily I ſee no probabilitie, I had almoſt ſaid, no poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, that they wil hereafter proue true and dutifull ſubiects to the King of <hi>great Britaine.</hi> They may well make proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and outward ſhewes, of loue, and duty, and obedience towards the Prince: but <hi>Lupus pilum, non ingenium mutat,</hi> a wolfe is a wolfe though hee bee cloathed in a ſheepe-skinne; well may hee caſt his old haire, but ſtill he keepes his own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Shal their faire ſpeeches make vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue them?</p>
            <q>—ſic notus Vlyſſes?</q>
            <p>Is the craft of the Romiſh foxes no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter knowne vnto vs?</p>
            <q>timeo Danaos, &amp; dona ferentes.</q>
            <p>I feare their fawning farre more, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their frowning, it was but a frivolous tale, which the people of <hi>Alexandria</hi> told <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy, etſi non communicamus tecum, tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amamus te,</hi> although we do not commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with thee, yet wee loue thee. For how can a man loue him in his hart, with whom he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not finde in his hart to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate?</p>
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:25300:68"/>
            <p>I am in a field, in which I might courſe at large, but I am mindfull of the time, &amp; will not preſume too long vpon your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience. Some of our worthies do ſtoutly with their pens oppoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues againſt theſe men, &amp; I pray God every magiſtrate in his place would be as careful in vnſhea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing the ſword of iuſtice againſt them.<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Catilin.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">a</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Habemus in eos Senatuſconſultum ſatis vehemens, &amp; grave;</hi> we haue an act, &amp; ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute ſtrong enough againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But their boldneſſe, not waining, but daily encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, makes me almoſt ſay, as it followeth in the oratour, <hi>habemus incluſum, in tabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, tanquam gladium in vaginâ reconditu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> It is cloſed in the book as a ſword in the ſcabbart, or (as<note n="b" place="margin">1. Sam. 21</note> 
               <hi>Goliahs</hi> ſword was) <hi>wrapt in a cloath behinde the Ephod.</hi> The beſt that I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay in this caſe, is to vſe the propheſie of the Crow in<note n="c" place="margin">Suet. in Domitiano.</note> 
               <hi>Suetonius,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, all will be well:
<q>Eſt benè non potuit dicere, dixit erit.</q>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Plin. nat. hiſt. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>16</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pliny</hi> writeth that the tricks of an ape, wil ſo vex &amp; moue a Lyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he wil diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorge, and caſt vp, whatſoever lies on his ſtomach. I doubt not but their apiſh tricks will in time moue the heart, &amp; ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, of our gracious, &amp; merciful <hi>Coeur
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:25300:68"/> de Lion,</hi> &amp; other magiſtrates in their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to caſt vp, and ſhew ſuch tokens of their inward griefe, as they ſhall haue iuſt occaſion to conceiue againſt them; and to purge the body politique fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xious humours wherewith it is endange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And without this there is no aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of peace. For as<note n="e" place="margin">2. King. 9.22.</note> 
               <hi>Iehu</hi> ſaid vnto <hi>Iehoram</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he went againſt the houſe of <hi>Ahab:</hi> is it peace <hi>Iehu!</hi> (ſaid <hi>Iehora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>) What peace ſaid the other, while the whoredomes of thy mother <hi>Iezabel,</hi> and her witchcraftes are great in number? So ſay I, what peace can bee expected, as long as the whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the <hi>Romiſh Iezabel,</hi> and her witchcrafts, and inchanting cups, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhee withdraweth the people from their obedience to their Soveraigne, and ſtealeth their harts from him (as did<note n="f" place="margin">2. Sam. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.6.</note> 
               <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolon</hi> the hearts of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> from <hi>David</hi> his father,) are in great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber. As long as the Pope can ſet any foot-hold in <hi>Britaine,</hi> he will ſtill beſtirre himſelfe to moleſt the peace of our <hi>Sion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Et ſi non aliquâ nocuiſſet, mortuus eſſet.</hi> But enough (if not too much) of this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect. It is a point which I vowed to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle; not out of any ſpleene to any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:25300:69"/> perſon whoſoever (hee that ſeeth the thoughts of my heart, knowes that I lie not) but for the loue of the truth, the zeale of Gods glory, the integritie of my conſcience, &amp; the diſcharge of my duty. And herein <hi>liberavi animam meam:</hi> look yee vnto it. The third propoſition fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p n="23">23 <hi>Yee ſhall die.)</hi> What mettall other creatures were made of, whether imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly of nothing, or of ſome preexiſtent matter, I finde no expreſſe mention in Gods booke. This I finde, that man was made of a matter, and that not gold, nor ſilver, pearle or pretious ſtones, but of earth, the baſeſt and vileſt of all the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yea of the duſt of the earth, even of drie duſt, which is good for nothing: that if hee ſhall with proud <hi>Phaeton</hi> in the Poet, boaſt that <hi>Apollo,</hi> God is his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hee might preſently call to minde, that poore <hi>Clymene,</hi> the earth is his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; that hee was<note n="g" place="margin">Gen. 2.7.</note> made of duſt, that hee is<note n="h" place="margin">Pſ. 103.14</note> but duſt, &amp; that<note n="i" place="margin">Gen. 3.19</note> hee ſhall returne to duſt. And yet I knowe not how it comes to paſſe, but I am ſure it is true, that many in autoritie reſemble the duſt in no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty better then one, that as the dry duſt
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:25300:69"/> in the ſtreets, is with every blaſt of wind blowne aloft into the aire: ſo are their hearts blowne aloft, and ſwelled vp with a windie tympanie of their owne great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But let them climbe as high as they can, God will one day ſend a ſhower, and lay this duſt. They are but naturall men; &amp; the threed of nature (as a Poet fayneth) is tyed vnto the foot of <hi>Iupiters</hi> chaire: he can looſe it, when it ſhall pleaſe him. Though <hi>Adams</hi> wit was ſuch, that hee could giue names vnto every creature, according to their natures, yet he forgot his own name. He did not remember that he was called <hi>Adam, homo ab humo,</hi> by reaſon of that affinitie that was between him and the earth. Theſe ſonnes of <hi>Adam</hi> are very like their old grandfather, they are wittie in ſeeking out the names, and properties of other creatures, but they forget their owne names, and their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures too. And this is the <hi>cauſe why they be ſo holden with pride, and overwhelmed with cruelties.</hi> They wil with<note n="k" place="margin">Iſ. 14.13.</note> 
               <hi>Nabuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar,</hi> ſtriue to advance themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the ſtarres of God; and to match their olde grandfather, the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> who though hee was made of earth, yet
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:25300:70"/> with the wings of pride and arrogancie would needs ſoare vp into heaven, and care little for reſembling their elder bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> who tooke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him our weakneſſe, that wee might bee ſtrengthned: our povertie, that we might be enriched; our nakedneſſe, that wee might bee cloathed; our baſeneſſe, that we might be exalted; our mortalitie, that we might bee inveſted in the robe of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie; and was contented to deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to earth, that he might make a way for vs, to aſcend from earth to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. But let them ſecure themſelues as much as they will; their houre-glaſſe is continually running; the tide of death will tarry no man. Our<note n="l" place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ec. 18.</note> 
               <hi>father hath eaten a ſower grape, and his childrens teeth are ſet on edge.</hi> Our gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dfather for eating of the forbidden tree, had this ſentence denounced againſt him; <hi>that he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to duſt.</hi> And his children are liable vnto it, till heauen and earth be renewed, and there be no more death.</p>
            <p>Thoſe gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at and mightie Gods of the earth, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch cloath themſelues<note n="m" place="margin">Luk. 16 19</note> 
               <hi>in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and fine linnen,</hi> and dwell in houſes of <hi>Cedar,</hi> and<note n="n" place="margin">Iſ. 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>adde houſe to houſe, and land
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:25300:70"/> to land,</hi> as if the way to heaven laid all by land, haue a time appointed them, when their inſatiable deſires ſhall bee conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a <hi>Golgotha,</hi> a place of dead mens skulls, a little portion of the great pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters field, as much as will ſerue to hide, &amp; cover a dead carkaſſe in it. You which ſit on the ſeat of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, whom the Lord hath ſo highly extolled as to bee called <hi>Gods,</hi> you haue your daies numbred, your months determined, your bounds ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed which yee cannot paſſe. It is not the ripeneſſe of your wits, nor the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of your places, nor the excellency of your learning, nor the largeneſſe of your commiſſion, that can adde one inch vnto the threed of your daies.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Hor. car. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Od. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note>Pallida mors aequo pulſat pede paupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum tabernas,</l>
               <l>Regum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> turres—</l>
            </q>
            <p>Deaths arrowe will as qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kly pierce through the ſtrong caſtle of a king, as the muddie wall of a countrie ſwaine. Were yee wiſer then <hi>Solomon,</hi> ſtronger then <hi>Sampſon,</hi> richer the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Iob,</hi> mightier then the greateſt mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arch of the earth, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuller in your places then <hi>Samuel,</hi> that faithfull Iudge of <hi>Iſrael;</hi>
               <q>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:25300:71"/>Ire tamen reſtat Numa quò devenit &amp; Ancus.</q> This muſt be the concluſion; <hi>Yee muſt die as men,</hi> and yeeld your bodies to deathes ſergeant, to be kept priſoners in the dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon of the earth, till the great and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Aſſiſes that ſhal be holden by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt, in the cloudes of the skie, at the laſt day. The concluſion is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, howſoever the premiſes be fallible, and doubtfull.<note n="p" place="margin">Seneca.</note> 
               <hi>Alexander,</hi> when by his followers hee was called a <hi>God,</hi> forgot that he was to die as a man, till by a poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned arrow hee was put in minde of his mortalitie, &amp; then he confeſſed the truth: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>os me Deum eſſe dixiſtis, ſed iam me ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem eſſe ſentio.</hi> You ſaid that I was a God, but now I perceiue I am but a man. And ſhortly after hee perceiued it with a witneſſe, when he was poiſoned by <hi>Antipater,</hi> and then incloſed in a ſmall parcell of ground, whoſe aſpiring minde the whole world could not fill.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Epitaph. Hen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Regi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Angl.</note>Cui ſatis ad votum non eſſent omnia terrae</l>
               <l>Climata, terra modò ſufficit octo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>He, whom the whole earth could not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:25300:71"/> was at length contented with a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of ground of eight, yea of ſix foote long.<note n="r" place="margin">Act. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Herod</hi> when vpon a day hee was arayed in royall apparell, and ſate on the bench, &amp; gaue ſuch an excellent charge, that the people cryed,
<q>—non vox hominem ſonat—</q> It is the voice of <hi>God,</hi> and not of man, im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mediatly after proued neither God nor man. For he was eaten vp of wormes, and gaue vp the Ghoſt. Rare examples for the <hi>Gods</hi> of the earth, to looke downe into their owne boſomes, and to remember that they <hi>muſt die as men.</hi> It is a good cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the <hi>Emperour</hi> of the <hi>Abyſſenes (Preſter Iohn)</hi> to haue every meal, for the firſt diſh, that comes on his table, a dead mans skul, to put him in mind of his mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie. So was that which was vſed by <hi>Philip:</hi> namely, to haue a boy every daie to put him in minde, that he was to die as a man. Not much vnlike was the old pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the<note n="ſ" place="margin">Munſt. Coſmogr.</note> 
               <hi>Egyptians,</hi> who when their Princes went to banquet, vſed to beare before them the picture of a dead man, to put them in mind of their mortalitie.</p>
            <p n="24">24 Seeing then that yee muſt die, ſtudy to haue your accounts in readineſſe, that
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:25300:72"/> whenſoever t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Lord ſhal cal you hence, he may finde you provided<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Be faithful in thoſe high <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es wherein God hath placed you.<note n="t" place="margin">2. Chr. 19 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Ye execute not the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of man, but of the Lord.</hi> Aske cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of God, &amp; weigh your proceedings in the ballance of the ſanctuary. Doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what God commands you, and the teſtimony of a good conſcience will warrant to be lawfull, remembring that yee m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt one day (God knowes howe ſoone that day will come) be ſummoned to appeare before the common Iudge of all fleſh; who is a burning, &amp;<note n="u" place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.</note> 
               <hi>conſuming fire,</hi> who is not blinded with ſec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et cloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, nor corrupted with bribes, nor mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with friends, nor allured by flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, nor perſwaded by the importunity of intreaters, to depart an haires breadth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the courſe of iuſtice: no though theſe<note n="a" place="margin">Ezech. 14 14.</note> three men <hi>Noah, Daniel,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iob,</hi> ſhoulde ſtand before him, and make interceſſion in your behalfe. Theſe things remember, and do, and ye ſhall haue comfort in your liues, comfort at your deaths. And when your ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſhall be removed from thoſe earthly co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ges wherin they now dwel, they ſhalbe tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>verlaſting ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:25300:72"/> and received with this ioyfull, and comfortable welcome:<note n="b" place="margin">Mat 25.21.</note> 
               <hi>it is wel done good ſervants and faithfull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yee haue beene fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thfull in a little, I will make you rulers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver much; enter into your maſters ioy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="25">25 <hi>Like men]</hi> It is implyed in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of my text, that <hi>it is the lot &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of all men to die.</hi> And therefore as it concernes magiſtrates, ſo it concernes al others to provide the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues for their end, becauſe<note n="c" place="margin">Eccl. 11.3.</note> 
               <hi>as the tree fals, ſo it lies:</hi> that is, as the day of death ſhall leaue them, ſo the day of iudgement ſhall finde them.</p>
            <p>Remember this yee that are to be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,<note place="margin">Application. <hi>1.</hi> to witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſes, &amp;c.</note> for giving teſtimony vnto the truth, and iurers for giving a verdict ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the truth. And as you loue &amp; revere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the truth it ſelfe, as ye deſire the benefit of your Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brethren, which yee ſhould loue as your ſelues, as ye wiſh the glory of God, which ye ſhould tender more then your ſelues; let it be a forcible motiue vnto you to deale vprightly in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very cauſe with every man, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining to the right hand, or to the left, then ſhall yee ſanctifie the name of God, by whom yee do ſweare to ſpeake truely, to deale truely: ye ſhall giue occaſion to
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:25300:73"/> good men to praiſe God for you, and yee ſhall not neede to bee aſhamed to meete God in the face, when he ſhall cal you to a reckoning for your doings. But on the other ſide, if rewards ſhall blind you, or feare enforce you, or pitty moue you, or partiality ſway you, or any reſpect what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever draw you to ſmoother the truth, and favour an evill cauſe: yee pearce your ſelues through with many darts. For firſt you are falſe witneſſes againſt your neighbour: ſecondly, ye are theeues, yee rob him of his right: thirdly, yee are mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, yee kill him in his body, or in his name, or in his maintenance: fourthly, &amp; which is worſt of all, ye take the name of your God in vaine, yea as much as in you lyeth, yee take his godhead from him, &amp; make him who is the trueth from everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, to be all one with the devill, who is a lyar from the beginning. If yee muſt be countable vnto God, when he ſhall call you hence, for every <hi>idle worde that goes out of your mouthes;</hi> and if the leaſt vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly thought of your harts, in the rigour of Gods iuſtice, deſerue eternall death, how ſhal ye be able to ſtand in iudgement vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derous <hi>Chaos</hi> of ſo many cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:25300:73"/> ſinnes. I cannot proſecute this point: only for concluſion I ſay with<note n="d" place="margin">Deut. 30.19 20.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes, behold this day haue I ſet before you life &amp; death, bleſſing and curſing, chooſe life, &amp; ye ſhall liue.</hi> If not, <hi>I pronounce vnto you this daie, ye ſhall ſurely periſh. The mouth of the Lord hath spoken it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="26">26 You,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> To lawyers Atturnies, &amp;c.</note> whoſe profeſſion is to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cauſes in controverſie, &amp; by your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the laws to diſtinguiſh between right and wrong, truth and falſhood, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that ye muſt die. And therefore I beſeech you in the feare of God, to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to make the cauſe of your clients ſure, as that yee do not in the meane time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get <hi>S.</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">2. Pet. 1.10</note> 
               <hi>Peters</hi> counſell, <hi>to make your owne election ſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I vrge this the rather, becauſe <hi>(—abſit reverentia vero)</hi> I will ſpeake the truth in deſpite of all ſcoffes, &amp; I hope ſuch as are ingenuous wil beare with my plainenes, if as<note n="f" place="margin">Plut. Apot.</note> 
               <hi>Philip</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Macedonians,</hi> I call a boat a boat, and a ſpade a ſpade; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſeemeth to bee much neglected by many of your profeſſion, who with <hi>Martha</hi> trouble themſelues about many buſineſſes, but <hi>vnum neceſſarium,</hi> to meet Chriſt, and talke with him, they ſcarce re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:25300:74"/> it. I remember the ſaying of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mades</hi> touching the <hi>Athenians,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they refuſed to make <hi>Alexander</hi> one of their Gods, &amp; <hi>Caſſander</hi> (who was his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour) threatned that vnleſſe they woulde doe it, hee woulde preſently overthrowe their city: the <hi>Athenians</hi> (ſaid <hi>Demades</hi>) haue reaſon to looke to themſelues, leaſt, while they are too curious about heaven, they looſe the earth. But theſe men haue need to looke to themſelues, leaſt while they trouble themſelues too much about the earth they looſe heaven: by whoſe meanes eſpecially it is effected, that our courts, do too much reſemble the Lyons den, which howſoever other beaſts in ſimplicity went flocking on heapes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, yet the foxe, that found by experience how others ſped, durſt not come neere it.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Quia me veſtigia te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t <hi>(ſaid ſhee)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Omnia te adverſum spectantia nulla re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trorſum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>All comes to them, little from them: they haue as attractiue a force ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſilver, as the loadſtone hath for yron.<note n="g" place="margin">Hom. Iliad lib. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Glaucus</hi> made no good market with <hi>Diomedes,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he changed his golden armour, for armour of braſſe: but many clients co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaine that
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:25300:74"/> they meet with worſer merchants, who for a purſe ful of angels giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing but a blacke boxe full of papers. Procra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinations, &amp; vnneceſſary delaies, for fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the lawyers coffers, and pilling of the poore clients, is a fault which I haue glanced at heretofore, and might a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times hereafter yer ever it be refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. For never was it more ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt then now, &amp; never was it ſo much practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as now. Well fare the old <hi>Athenian</hi> lawes, which (as <hi>Anacharſis</hi> once ſaid) were like vnto ſpider-webs, that catched the little flies, and let the waſpe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d the Bee, and the Beetle burſt through them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in reſpect of them that hold w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>p, &amp; B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, and Beetle and al, and ſcarce any ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urſt through them. But what do I now? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne I the law? I do wrong. <hi>Is the law ſinne?</hi> ſaith<note n="h" place="margin">Rom 7.6 7.12 14.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> (he ſpeaks of the moral law.) <hi>Nay the law is holy, and iuſt, and good, but I am carnall, ſold vnder ſinne.</hi> So ſay I, is our law ſin? Nay our law is iuſt, &amp; good. Here is the breaknecke of all: too many of our ſolliciters, atturnies, &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſcribes, are merely carnal &amp; ſold vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſin, vſing it not to that end for which it is ordeined, the glory of God, and the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:25300:75"/> peace of the commonwealth, but as the fowler doth his not, for catching of plo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers to inrich themſelues withal: making that which ſhoulde bee for the common good, a <hi>monopolie</hi> for themſelues, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of mockerie, and a meere ſhop of moſt horrible, &amp; deteſtable covetouſnes.</p>
            <p>But it is the worſt thriving in the world to riſe with an other mans fall. It was a ſhort, but a ſharpe quip, which a captiue gaue vnto <hi>Pompey</hi> the great, <hi>Noſtrâ miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riâ es Magnus,</hi> It is our miſery that gaue thee thy ſurname. It is ſo in this caſe, <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrâ miſera es magnus,</hi> may the clie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſay to his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſellor. As the ſwelling of the <hi>ſplene</hi> argueth the conſumption of other parts: ſo the inriching of the lawyer, the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſhing of the client. If the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his cauſe be good (alas) why is it never ended? If it be nought, why is it ſtill defended? If the cauſe be nought, the defence is worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nought. Vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d me rightly: it may be a Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſellours hap to be a ſpeaker in an ill cauſe, and yet he not worthie any blame. The party may miſinforme him in the truth of the cauſe. Iudgements in the like caſe may be different, or ſome other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance may deceiue him. But where it plainely appeares to be nought indeed,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:25300:75"/> by nimbleneſſe of wit, and volubility of tongue, to ſmooth it over with coloura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble probabilities, thereby (as far as thou canſt) to giue the truth an overthrow, this is but to guild over a rotten poſt, <hi>to call good evill, and evill good,</hi> to let looſe <hi>Barabbas,</hi> and deſtroy <hi>Ieſus,</hi> to make the devill, who is a feend of darknes, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the likenes of an <hi>angell</hi> of light, and therefore worſe then nought. Better with <hi>Papinian</hi> to haue thy head parted from thy ſhoulders, then to be a commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Advocate in ſuch cauſes.</p>
            <p>There is a kind of men in the worlde, who though they know before they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin their ſuits, or at leaſt before they haue waded far in them, as well as they know their owne names, &amp; the number of their fingers, that the matter which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute, by extremitie of law, is manifeſt wrong: yet either out of a malitious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, to giue their adverſaries an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, or becauſe their abilitie is ſuch, that it will hold them out, or becauſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe ioine with them, and make it a common quarrell, or becauſe they loue (<hi>Salamander</hi>-like) to bee broyling in the fire of contention, can by no meanes bee
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:25300:76"/> diſſwaded from their wicked enterpriſe. This matter ſo wickedly, &amp; miſchievouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begun, one counſellour or other, (that loues (with the eele-catchers in the olde comedie) to bee fiſhing in muddie wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and deſires alife to bath himſelfe in any poole that an Angell ſhall trouble) muſt manage. He muſt finde ſome proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble title in the lawe for it: hee muſt as long as the lawe will afford him any kinde of weft, weaue it out in length, and when it failes, hee muſt ſpider-like ſpinne it out of his owne bowels. Hee muſt prolong iudgment, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the matter fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one day to an other, from one tearme to an other, from one yeare to an other, from one court to an other; till at length hee who hath both God, and the law, and a good conſcience on his ſide, for very wearineſſe, be enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to giue it over, or be brought to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame beggary, that hee can follow his ſuit no longer, or till <hi>Atropos</hi> haue cut in ſunder the threed of his daies, &amp; ſo made an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd of the quarrell. Well were it for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monwealth if ſuch ſeditious quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rellers, and make-bates were by ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere puniſhment, taught not to delude
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:25300:76"/> iuſtice, and oppreſſe the truth: that others by their example might be terrified from ſuch wicked attempts, and that honeſt &amp; godly men might liue in more peace, and t a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quillity. If my words do ſound harſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the eares of ſome of my hearers, I muſt ſay of them as<note n="i" place="margin">Hierom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaith of ſome in his epiſtle to <hi>Ruſticus: dum mihi iraſcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſuam indicant conſcientiam, multo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> peiùs de ſe, quàm de me iudicant.</hi> If they be offended with me, they bewray their own guilty conſciences, and haue a farre worſe opinion of themſelues, then they haue of me. I name none; I know none. I ſpeake in generall againſt ſinne, <hi>and</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.20.</note> 
               <hi>if any mans conſcience condemne him, God is greater then his conſcience, and knoweth all things,</hi> and therefore<note n="l" place="margin">Ioh. 5.14</note> 
               <hi>let him goe his way, and ſinne no more, leaſt a worſe thing happen vnto him.</hi> My hope is that all of you are of a better diſpoſition. But I knowe yee are all men, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſubiect to the like paſſions, &amp; infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities that others are. Let mee therefore once againe (to returne to that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which I haue a little digreſſed) beſeech you in all your pleadings, &amp; legall proceedings to remember that account, that yee muſt
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:25300:77"/> make vnto God, when yee ſhall bee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led hence. Remember that there is a woe denounced againſt them<note n="m" place="margin">Iſ. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>that call good evill, and evill good.</hi> Remember the end of your profeſſion; it is not to ſowe diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to fill your own coffers, to make a mart to vtter your owne wares, to ſhewe your ready wits, and voluble tongues in ſpeaking probably of every ſubiect good or bad: but to helpe every man to his right, to cut away ſtrife and contention, and to reſtore peace and vnitie in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, that all the members of the body politicke may be of one heart, and one ſoule.<note n="n" place="margin">Eph. 4.4, 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>Even as there is one hope of our vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, one Lord, one faith one baptiſme, one God, and father of all, which is aboue all and through all, and in vs all.</hi> Remember that our God is called the<note n="o" place="margin">2. Cor 13 11.</note> 
               <hi>God of peace,</hi> his Goſpell, the<note n="p" place="margin">Eph 6.15</note> 
               <hi>Gospell of peace,</hi> his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters the<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſ.</hi> 52 7.</note> 
               <hi>Ambaſſadours of peace;</hi> his naturall ſonne, the<note n="r" place="margin">Coloſſ. 1.</note> author of <hi>peace,</hi> his adopted ſonnes, <hi>the children of peace:</hi> if then yee will bee the ſonnes of the moſt higheſt, your endeavour muſt be this,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Eph. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>to preſerue the vnitie of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.7</note> 
               <hi>Conſider what I ſay, &amp; the Lord
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:25300:77"/> giue you wiſdome, and vnderſtanding in all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally to ſpeake vnto all (and ſo to make an end of all) ſeeing that we are all tenants at will,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> To all.</note> and muſt be thruſt out of the doores, of theſe earthly tabernacles, whenſoever it ſhal pleaſe our great land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord to call vs hence: let vs <hi>haue our loines girt, and our lampes continually burning,</hi> that whenſoever the Lord ſhall call vs hence, in the evening, or in the morning, at noone-day, or at mid-night, hee may find vs ready. <hi>Happy is that man whom his maſter when he comes, ſhall find watching.</hi> Let vs every day ſumme vp our accounts with God.<note n="u" place="margin">Hierom.</note> 
               <hi>Ita aedificemus quaſi ſemper victuri, ita vivamus quaſi cras morituri:</hi> let vs build as if wee would ever liue, but let vs liue, as if we were ever ready to dy. Then may every one of vs in the integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of heart, and ſynceritie of conſcience, when the time of his departing is at hand ſay with the bleſſed Apoſtle, <hi>I haue fought a good fight, and haue finiſhed my courſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4 7.8.</note> 
               <hi>I haue kept the faith; Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence forth is laid vp for me a crowne of righteouſneſſe, which God, the righteous Iudge ſhall giue mee at that day.</hi> Vnto this God, one eternal, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:25300:78"/> and vnchangeable <hi>Iehovah</hi> in eſſence, three perſons in manner of ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, the Father, the Son, and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, be aſcribed all honour, &amp; glory, power, might, and maieſtie, both now &amp; forevermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:25300:78"/>
            <head>The Principall points handled in the firſt Sermon.</head>
            <list>
               <item>The wicked abſtaine from ſin when a fit opportunitie is wanting. Sect. 1. 2. 3. 4.</item>
               <item>The danger of covetouſneſſe. Sect. 5. 6. 7. 8.</item>
               <item>Hypocrites are alwaies mingled with godly profeſſours. Sect. 11. 12.</item>
               <item>Foure Iudaſſes in theſe times. Sect. 14.</item>
               <item>The firſt the ſimonical Patron. Sect. 15. 16. 17.</item>
               <item>The ſecond the oppreſſour. Sect. 18. 19.</item>
               <item>The third the briber. Sect. 20.</item>
               <item>The fourth the deceitfull lawyer. Sect. 21.</item>
               <item>The Magiſtrats dutie. Sect. 22.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>The principall points handled in the ſecond Sermon.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Magiſtrats haue their authoritie from God. Sect. 4.</item>
               <item>Which makes againſt the Anabaptiſts Sect. 5.</item>
               <item>The Popes vſurped power over ſecular Princes. Sect. 6. 7.</item>
               <item>Magiſtrats be Gods deputies. Sect. 8.</item>
               <item>Therefore ſubiects muſt honour them whether they be good or bad. Sect. 9. 10. 11.</item>
               <item>Magiſtrats doe often abuſe their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. Sect. 12.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:25300:79"/>
               <item>How carefull they ſhould bee of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging their duties. Eſpecially in main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taining true religion. Sect. 14. 15. 16. 17.</item>
               <item>Papiſts are not to bee ſuffered, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their differences from vs in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of religion. Sect. 18. 19.</item>
               <item>And becauſe there is no probability that they will bee true ſubiects. Sect. 20. 21. 22.</item>
               <item>Iudges muſt remember that they muſt die &amp; then be iudged. Sect. 23.</item>
               <item>The great abuſe of the lawes. Sect. 26.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:25300:79"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
